<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The geometrical sea-man: or, the art of navigation performed by geometry. Shewing how all the three kinds of sayling, viz. by the plain chart, by Mercators chart, by a great circle. may be easily and exactly performed by a plain ruler and a pair of compasses, without arithmeticall calculation. / By Henry Phillippes.</title>
            <author>Phillippes, Henry, d. 1677?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E652_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205892</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865125</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865125</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 100:E652[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The geometrical sea-man: or, the art of navigation performed by geometry. Shewing how all the three kinds of sayling, viz. by the plain chart, by Mercators chart, by a great circle. may be easily and exactly performed by a plain ruler and a pair of compasses, without arithmeticall calculation. / By Henry Phillippes.</title>
                  <author>Phillippes, Henry, d. 1677?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert and William Leybourn, for George Hurlock, and are to be sold at his shop at Magnus Church-corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The second "1" in imprint is crossed out and altered to "1651"; "Febr. 1.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Wing (2nd ed.) P2044.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Navigation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117362:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GEOMETRICAL SEA-MAN: OR, THE ART OF NAVIGATION Performed by <hi>GEOMETRY.</hi> SHEWING How all the three kinds of Sayling, <hi>viz.</hi> By the Plain Chart, By <hi>Mercators</hi> Chart, By a Great Circle. May be eaſily and exactly performed by a Plain Ruler and a pair of Compaſſes, without <hi>Arithmeticall Calculation.</hi> By HENRY PHILLIPPES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by ROBERT and WILLIAM LEYBOURN, for GEORGE HURLOCK, and are to be ſold at his Shop at <hi>Magnus</hi> Church-corner, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117362:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117362:2"/>
            <head>TO The INGENIOUS, INDUSTRIOUS, and Yonger SEA-MEN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is chiefely for your profit that I write; ſo I hope, that though I ſhall be condemned of others, yet I ſhall gain your pardon. I confeſſe my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour may ſeeme needleſſe, after ſo many learned Authots, to ſet forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of this ſubject. And it may be accounted a preſumptious folly for any to goe about to teach Sea-men in their Art, eſpecially in theſe times, wherein there were never more, nor more skilfull Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But in anſwer hereto take notice of theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That many Books of this ſubject, though they are plain and eaſie for all Sea-men to underſtand, yet they are not ſo exact and perfect in all things as they ought to be.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117362:3"/>
            <p>Secondly; That though Mr. <hi>Wright,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gunter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Norwood,</hi> have very fully ſhewed the errours of the foreſaid Books, and have very perfectly reformed them; yet their Books are not plain and uſefull for all men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they require much knowledge in Arithmetick.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though there be many skilfull Sea-men, which are able to make uſe of theſe Authors; yet there are many others, who would willingly attain to a more perfect knowledge in this Art, and yet cannot, for want of Arithmetick. Now for the helpe of ſuch as theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, have I publiſhed this Book: wherein you ſhall finde how all that which is to be performed by Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick in the foreſaid Authors, may be ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly perform'd by Geometry with the Ruler and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes; ſo that any one that can but read and write a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, though he have no skill in Arithmetick, may hereby attain a true and perfect knowledge of the Art of Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, ſo that he ſhall be able to keepe as true and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an account of his Voyage in any part of the World, as one that works by the moſt exact rules of Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. Nay, I dare ſay, that one that can neither write nor read, yet being of an ingenious capacity; and having one to teach him according to this way, may attain ſufficient skill in this Art.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This may alſo be uſefull to thoſe who can performe theſe things by Arithmetick, and the Doctrine of plain Triangles: For by this way they may perform them far more eaſily and readily, and almoſt as exactly. And though ſuch men may know many of theſe things already, yet perhaps they may gain ſome knowledge hereby.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As by this way the knowledge of the Art is
<pb facs="tcp:117362:3"/> moſt eaſily and ſpeedily attained, ſo it is more certainly and conſtantly retained and preſerved, both in reſpect of the knowledge and practice thereof. Firſt, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hereof is more certainly retained in your memory: for this is the reaſon why all Authors are forced to make uſe of ſome Geometricall figures; partly to explain their Rules, and partly to fixe them in the memory, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them viſible to the eye; for we more ſurely remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber any thing which we ſee done, then what we only hear. Now in this way, every thing is made much more viſible to the eye, and therefore more eaſie both to learn and remember. Secondly, the practice of this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge will be more ſurely and conſtantly preſerved: for Arithmeticall calculations require many Tables, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Sines, Tangents, Secants, Meridian,</hi> which cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be kept in memory; ſo that if by any croſs accident a Sea-man be deprived of his Books, he can make no uſe of his skill in Arithmetick. But if a man knowes how to performe theſe things by Geometry, though all his Books and Writings be loſt, yet having but a plain Ruler and a pair of Compaſſes, he may quickly recover his loſs, and fall to his work as before.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe conſiderations, I have adventured to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this little Book, wherein I have briefely and plainly laid down the whole Art (as to the Geometricall part thereof) beginning at the firſt principles, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding by degrees to the higheſt concluſions. I have uſed the more figures to make every thing the plainer. And I have provided ſuch figures, as ſerve not only for demonſtration of the thing, but may ſerve for Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to work upon; or you may eaſily, by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons given, make the like. To conclude, I have ſtudyed
<pb facs="tcp:117362:4"/> to make thoſe things plaineſt, which have at any time moſt troubled my ſelfe to underſtand. So that I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not but that any one that is induſtrious, may here of eaſily and ſpeedily attain, ſuch a competent meaſure by knowledge in this Art, that by Gods bleſſing upon his ſtudy and labour therein, he may obtain much credit and profit. Which is all the deſire, of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your well meaning Friend</hi> Henry Phillippes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:117362:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS AND order of the whole BOOK.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the two firſt Chapters is ſhewed how to perform ſome <hi>Geometricall Principles;</hi> which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known, becauſe moſt of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work is done thereby.</item>
               <item>The third Chapter ſhews the making and uſe of the plain Chart, being the common way of ſayling.</item>
               <item>The fourth Chapter ſhews the making and uſe of the true Sea-Chart, being in many reſpects more perfect then the former.</item>
               <item>The fifth Chapter ſhews the way of ſayling by a great Circle; being the moſt exact and beſt way of ſayling that can be.</item>
               <item>The ſixth Chapter ſhews many uſefull obſervations in all theſe kinds of ſayling.</item>
               <item>The ſeventh Chapter ſhews another way of ſayling by the arch of a great Circle.</item>
               <item>he laſt Chapter ſhews how to keepe a perfect account of any Voyage by a little common Arithmetick, <hi>viz.</hi> Addition and Subſtraction.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:117362:5"/>
            <head>The names of ſuch Books as are printed and ſold by <hi>George Hurlock,</hi> at <hi>Magnus</hi> Church corner.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Seamans Kalendar.</item>
               <item>The enemie of Idleneſſe, teaching how to endite Epiſtles &amp; Letters in <hi>4</hi> Books, <hi>83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Normans</hi> Art of Tens, or Decimall Arithmetick, <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Art of Navigation by <hi>Martin Curtis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Safeguard of Saylors, or great Rutter, by <hi>Robert Norman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Table of Gauging all manner of Veſſels, by <hi>John Goodwin, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Path way to perfect ſayling, by <hi>Richard Polter, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pitiſcus</hi> his Doctrine of Triangles, with a Canon of naturall <hi>Sines, Tangents,</hi> and <hi>Secants.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Norwood's</hi> Doctrine of Triangles, with <hi>Logarithmes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Norwood's</hi> Epitomie, applyed to plain and <hi>Mercators</hi> ſayling.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Norwoods</hi> ſea-mans practice.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Navigator,</hi> by Captain <hi>Charles Saltonſtall, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dary's</hi> deſcription and uſe of a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Quadrant, <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 16. A is wanting in the figure. <hi>page</hi> 33 <hi>line laſt, read</hi> A F, <hi>page</hi> 56 <hi>line</hi> 25. for 28 <hi>read</hi> 58, <hi>page</hi> 62, 67, 69. ſome words doubled may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> left out. <hi>page</hi> 70, <hi>line laſt, read,</hi> thereby know whether, &amp;c. <hi>page</hi> 80. <hi>laſt line of the Table,</hi> for 22 deg. <hi>read</hi> 33. <hi>page</hi> 88. <hi>in the Table, Col.</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> 1, 80, <hi>read</hi> 1,00. <hi>Col. laſt line</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> 0, 8, <hi>read.</hi> 0, 58.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="geometry_textbook">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117362:5"/>
            <head>THE GEOMETRICAL SEA-MAN. OR THE Art of <hi>Navigation</hi> performed by GEOMETRY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Containing ſome Geometricall Propoſitions, which will be of frequent uſe.</head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 1.</hi> How to erect a Perpendicular line at the end of a line.<note place="margin">The firſt <hi>Propoſition</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">What a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular line is.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Perpendicular line, is a line that ſtands directly upright from another line. As in the figure, the line B C is a perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular line, to the line A B. Now in the Figure there are two wayes of raiſing it, the one on the right ſide, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the left.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Let the line A B be given: and it is required to erect the line B C perpendicularly to it, at the end of the line in the point B.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Another way.</note>The ſecond way to perform this, is demonſtrated on the left ſide of the figure. Let the line A B be given as before, and it is required to erect the line A D perpendicularly in the point A.</p>
                  <p>To perform this, firſt, ſet one foot of your Compaſſes in any convenient point at pleaſure, as at L, and open the other foot to the point A, and draw the arch N A M, then lay your ruler to the center of this arch L, and the place where it croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the line A B, which is at N, and draw the line M L N, which doth croſſe the arch N A M in the point M. Laſtly, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Ruler to this croſſe at M, and the point A, draw the line D M A, ſo you ſhall have your deſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 2.</hi> To draw one line parallel to another line, at any diſtance required.<note place="margin">The ſecond <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">What is meant by a parallel line.</note>A Line is ſaid to be parallel to another line, when it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually diſtant from it in every part thereof. Thus in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117362:6"/> former figure the line P S is parallel to the line A B. Now the way to draw a parallel line is thus.</p>
                  <p>Let the line A B be the firſt line given, and it is required to draw the line P S parallel to it, according to the diſtance P A.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, open your Compaſſes to the diſtance you have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to uſe, which in this example is P A, then ſetting one foot in A, with the other draw the arch at P, and then keeping your Compaſſes at the ſame diſtance, remove one foot to B, and with the other draw the arch at S: laſtly, laying your ruler on the very edge of theſe two arches, draw the line P S, which will be parallel to A B, and ſo the propoſition is performed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 3.</hi> How to make a Geometricall Square.<note place="margin">The third <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Geometricall ſquare, is a ſquare whoſe foure ſides are all of one and the ſame length. Now in the firſt figure, let the line A B be the ſide of ſuch a Square, and it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make a Square of that length and breadth.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">How to make a Square.</note> you muſt draw the line A B according to the length given, then erect the perpendicular line A D at one end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as was ſhewed before, then ſetting one foot of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes in the corner A, open the other to B, and keeping one foot ſtill in A, with the other croſſe the perpendicular A D at D: then keeping your compaſſes at the ſame diſtance, ſet one foot in B, and with the other draw a ſhort arch at C, then ſet one foot at the croſſe at D, and with the other croſſe the arch laſt drawn in the point C: now if you draw lines through theſe marks, from A to D, from D to C, and from C to B, ſo you ſhall make the Geometricall Square A B C D as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  <p>If you will try your work whether you have made it true or no, then ſet one foot of your compaſſes in A,<note place="margin">How to try a Square.</note> and open the other to the corner at C, then with that diſtance, ſet one foot in B, and turn the other to the corner at D, if both theſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite corners have the ſame diſtance, the Square is truly made, otherwiſe not.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117362:7"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A long Square</note>If you would make a long ſquare, as the ſquare A P S B, firſt, you may draw the line P S parallel to A B, and according to the length of the ſide of your ſquare, then erect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular either at A or B, and draw the oppoſite ſide, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel thereunto, according as the length of your ſquare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: and you may try the truth of this ſquare, alſo by the oppoſite corners as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 4.</hi> To raiſe a perpendicular in the midſt of a line.<note place="margin">The fourth. <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN this ſecond figure, let A B be the line given; and it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to raiſe a perpendicular in the point C.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <note place="margin">The ſecond figure.</note>Firſt, ſet one foot of your compaſſes in the point C, and open the other to any diſtance at pleaſure, and marke the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven line therewith on both ſides from C, at the points A and B, then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in the point A, open the other to any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance you pleaſe beyond C, and draw a little arch above the line at F. Then with the ſame diſtance, ſet one foot in B, and with the other croſſe, the arch F with the arch D. Laſtly, lay your ruler to this croſſe, and the point C, and draw the line G C, which is perpendicular to the line A B, in the point C as was required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117362:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 5.</hi> From a point aloft, to let fall a perpendicular upon a line given.<note place="margin">The fifth <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>LEt G be the point aloft, from whence it is required to let fall a perpendicular upon the line A B in the ſecond fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſet one foot of your compaſſes in the point given, which is G, and open your compaſſes ſo wide that you may draw the arch A H B, which may cut the line A B in the points A and B, and the farther theſe two points are aſunder ſo much the better, then keeping your compaſſes at this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; ſet one foot in A, and with the other draw the arch E, then remove one foot to B, and croſſe the laſt arch at E, laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, laying your ruler to the point G, and this croſſe at E, draw the line G C E, ſo you have performed the propoſition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 6.</hi> To draw a line ſquire wiſe to another line.<note place="margin">The ſixth <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the ſecond figure let A B be the line given, and it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to draw the line G E ſquire wiſe to it, ſo that it may croſſe it at right angles.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, open your compaſſes at pleaſure, and ſetting one foot in the line at B, with the other make two ſhort arches, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the line at D, and the other below the line at E. Then with the ſame diſtance, ſet one foot in A, and with the other croſſe the two former arches at D and E. Laſtly, laying your ruler by theſe two croſſes D and E, draw the line G E, which will croſſe the line A B at right angles as was required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 7.</hi> To divide a line given into two equall parts.<note place="margin">The ſeventh <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the ſecond figure let A B be the line given, to be divided into two equal parts.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſet one foot of your compaſſes at the one end of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117362:8"/> the line at A, and open the other to any diſtance above half the line, &amp; therewith draw two little arches one above the line at F, and the other below the line at E, then remove your Compaſſes to B the other end of the line, and croſſe the two former arches at F and E, then lay your ruler to theſe two croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes F and E, and draw the line GC E, which will divide the line A B in two equal parts in the point C, ſo that A C is the one halfe, and C B the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 8.</hi> To raiſe a Perpendicular at the end of a line another way.<note place="margin">The eighth <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN this figure, let the line given be A B, and it is required to raiſe a perpendicular at the end thereof at B.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Here you may note that if the three ſides of a Triangle be made of theſe three numbers 3 4 5, or any other numbers that are proportionable thereunto, as 6 8 10, 9 12 15, 12 16 20, 30 40 50, it will have one right angle, which will be oppoſite to the greateſt ſide, as in the Triangle D B E, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117362:8"/> ſide E B is 3, the ſide B D is 4, and the ſide D E is 5, and the angle at B is a right angle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 9.</hi> To make one angle equall, or like to another.<note place="margin">The ninth <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>AN angle is the ioyning or croſſing of two lines:<note place="margin">What an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle is, with the generall kinds of angles.</note> if the two lines croſſe one another, or joyn one to another perpendicularly, then they are ſaid to make a right an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, or angles: if two lines meet or croſſe one another any other way, they are ſaid to make an oblique angle or angles.</p>
                  <p>Thus in the third figure, the lines D B and E B meeting in the point B, make a right angle. And in the ſecond figure, the lines A B and G E, croſſing one another in the point C, make four right angles, or quadrants. But in the third figure, the lines E D and B D, meeting in the point D, are ſaid to make an oblique angle. Now theſe oblique angles, if they be leſſe then a right angle, they are called acute or ſharpe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles: if they be more then a right angle, they are called ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſe or blunt angles.</p>
                  <p>Now for example of the propoſition, let the angle E D B be the appointed angle, and it is required to make the angle D B C like unto it.</p>
                  <p>In this example, becauſe the line D B is limited, and is common to both the angles, you ſhall need onely to ſet one foot of your compaſſes in B, and open the other to the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt diſtance of the line D E, which you may do by drawing the little arch which toucheth the line between 3 and 4: then remove your compaſſes to D, and draw the like arch at C, then lay your Ruler to the point B, and the very edge of this arch C, and draw the line B C, ſo ſhall the two angles be of one quantity or wideneſſe, as was deſired.</p>
                  <p>In other caſes this way will not ſerve, but this is ſufficient for the preſent purpoſe, and I ſhall ſhew you other wayes to perform that in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117362:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 10.</hi> To divide a line into any number of equall parts.<note place="margin">The tenth <hi>Propoſition</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the third figure, let the line B D be given, to be divided into four equall parts.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, from the end D, draw a line as D E, making an angle with the line D B at pleaſure, then from the other end of the line B make the angle D B C equall to the former an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, as was ſhewed in the laſt Propoſition. Then from the point D ſet off with your compaſſes, ſuch a number of any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, as lacks one of the number deſired, which in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, therefore muſt be 3, ſet off therefore on the line D E three equall parts 1, 2, and 3; then you muſt with the ſame diſtance of your compaſſes ſet off 1, 2, and 3, from the point B, on the line B C, then draw croſſe lines from the laſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the one line, to the firſt in the other, that is from 3 to 1, from 2 to 2, &amp;c. and theſe lines will divide the line B D into four equall parts as was deſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 11.</hi> To bring any three points, not lying in a ſtraight line, into a Circle.<note place="margin">The eleventh <hi>Propoſition</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN this figure, let A B C be the three points given, and it is required to draw a circle through them all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <note place="margin">The fourth figure.</note>Set one foot of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes in the middle point at B, and open your compaſſes to any diſtance you pleaſe, ſo it be above half the diſtance, between B, and either of the other marks (yea, it is no matter if need be, though it reach almoſt to, or quite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the neereſt of the other marks) and draw the arch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117362:9"/> D E F G, then keeping your compaſſes at this diſtance, ſet one foot in A, and with the other draw the arch G F, which croſſeth the former arch at G and F, then ſet one foot of your compaſſes in the third point C, and with the other draw the arch E D, which croſſeth the firſt arch at E and D, then laying your ruler to the interſections of theſe arches; draw the lines G F H and D E H, which will croſſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the point H, this croſſe at H, is the center of the Circle: therefore ſetting one foot of your compaſſe in this croſſe at H, open the other to any of the three points A B or C, and draw the circle; which if you have done well, will paſſe through all the three points A B C as was required.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Shewing how to divide a Circle ſeveral wayes which will be needful for many things.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt uſuall diviſion of a Circle, is into 24 equall parts, according to the 24 houres of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall day; which is thus to be performed.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of compass points</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Secondly, another uſuall and neceſſary diviſion of a circle is to divide a circle into 360 equall parts.<note place="margin">To divide a circle into 360 degrees.</note> For in all queſtion of Aſtronomy, and in the calculation of all triangles, theſe parts are the meaſure of the angles; ſo that every arch in this reſpect is ſuppoſed to be divided into 360 equall parts, which are called degrees, and each degree is ſuppoſed to be divided into 60 leſſer parts called minutes. To divide a circle after this manner, the ready way is thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, draw a line at pleaſure, and croſſe it at right angles with another line, and draw a circle as before, then keeping your compaſſes at this diſtance, divide the circle from the four quarters into 12 equall parts as before, then cloſing your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes divide each of theſe 12 parts into 3, ſo you ſhall have in all 36 parts, then you may eaſily with your pen divide each of theſe parts into 10 little parts, each of which ſtands for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and ſo you may number them as in the middle circle of the figure.</p>
               <p>A third uſuall diviſion of a circle is into 32 equall parts<note place="margin">To divide a circle into 32 parts.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of the points of the compaſſe, which may be thus performed.</p>
               <p>Firſt, draw the line of Eaſt and Weſt, and croſſe it at right angles with the line of North and South, and draw the circle as before, then keeping your compaſſes at that diſtance, ſet one foot where the line of Eaſt doth croſſe the circle, and with the other draw two little arches one above at B, and the other below at D: then with the ſame diſtance of your compaſſes ſet one foot where the line of weſt doth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117362:11"/> croſſe the circle, and draw two little arches like the former at A and C: then with the ſame diſtance of your compaſſes, ſet one foot where the line of North doth croſs the circle, and with the other, croſſe the two upper arches at A and B: then ſet one foot where the line of South doth croſſe the circle, and with the other croſſe the two lower arches at C and D; then laying your ruler croſſe-wayes to theſe croſſes, draw the lines A D and B C: ſo the circle ſhall be divided into eight equall parts; then cloſing your compaſſes, you may eaſily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide each of theſe 8 parts into 4, (for having divided one of them they will all fall out alike) and ſo you ſhall have the 32 rumbes or points of the compaſſe, which you may ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide if you pleaſe into halues and quarters, and draw the lines, and by three or four letters expreſſe their names as in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, which ſignifie as followeth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">The names of the 32 points of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe.</note>
                     <hi>North</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North by Weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-North-weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-weſt by North</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-weſt by Weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weſt-North-weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weſt by North</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weſt by South</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weſt-South-weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-weſt by Weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-weſt by South</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-South-weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South by Weſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South by Eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-South-eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-eaſt by South</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South-eaſt by Eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eaſt-South-eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eaſt by South</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eaſt by North</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eaſt-North-eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-eaſt by Eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-eaſt by North</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North-North-eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North by Eaſt</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To make an angle of any quantity.</note>Having thus divided a circle into theſe three ſorts of parts, it will be very uſefull to you in the dividing of any other circle, quadrant, or arch, and by this circle you may eaſily draw any angle of what quantity you pleaſe.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117362:11"/>
               <p>For example, let A B be a line given, and it is required to draw another line from the point A, ſo that it may make an angle of 45 degrees.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>In like manner ſuppoſing the line A B to be the Meridian or South line, and it is required to draw a line from the point A,<note place="margin">Another Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</note> which ſhal repreſent the Southeaſt or the fourth Rumbe from the Meridian.</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſet one foot of your compaſſes in the center of your divided circle, and extend the other to that circle which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into Rumbes; and with that diſtance draw the arch B C. Then ſetting one foot of your Compaſſes in that point where the South line and the circle croſſe each other, open the other to the line of Southeaſt, and then ſet off that diſtance from B to C in this laſt figure, then draw the line A C which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Southeaſt as was deſired.</p>
               <p>You may doe this alſo by a Scale of degrees, and Rumbes,<note place="margin">To make a Scale of Chords and Rumbs.</note> which you may have upon a ſtraight line on your ruler, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117362:12"/> you may thus make. Firſt, ſet one foot of your compaſſes in the center of the divided circle, and open the other to that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which parts the diviſions of the degrees and rumbes, and ſet off this diſtance on a ſtraight line upon your ruler, and marke very well with ſome ſpeciall marke, where this diſtance begins and ends, for this is your Radius or diſtance, which you muſt always take to draw your firſt arch withall, it being the ſixth part of a circle, or 60 degrees. Then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes where the circle, which is divided into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and rumbes doth croſſe the line of North or South, open the other to 10 degrees in that circle, and then transferre that diſtance into your Scale, then again, take out the diſtance of 20 degrees out of the circle, and transferre that likewiſe into your Scale, and ſo do for 30, 40, 50, 70, 80, 90 degrees. Always ſetting one foot in the place where the line of North or South doth croſſe the circle, and opening the other to the degree deſired. And in like manner when you transfer theſe diſtances into your ruler, you muſt always ſet one foot of your compaſſes at the beginning of the line, and with the other mark the diſtance in the line. And thus alſo you may take out the diſtances of the Rumbes, and ſet them upon a line on your ruler, and ſo having made your Scale, you may draw out any angle by it, as well as by the circle, and it will be ſomewhat more ready.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Example.</note>Now if you would draw the foreſaid angle of 45 degrees by this Scale, you muſt firſt ſet one foot of your compaſſes in the beginning of your Scale, and open the other to 60 degrees, which is the <hi>Radius</hi> of your Scale, and therewith draw the firſt arch B C, then ſetting one foot in the beginning of the Scale again, open the other to 45 degrees, and with that diſtance, ſetting one foot in B, croſſe the firſt arch at C, and then draw the line A C, as in the former example and figure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117362:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Shewing how to make a plain Chart, and many Propoſitions of ſayling by it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He drawing of the plain Chart, and the way of ſailing thereby, is the moſt plain and eaſie of all others. And though it be fit to be uſed, only in places neer the Equinoctial, or in ſhort Voyages: yet it will ſerve, for a good introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to that which follows, and this will not be loſt labour, for the ſame kind of work (with ſome cautions) muſt be obſerved in all kinds of Sailing.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The deſcription and making of the plain Chart.<note place="margin">The deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the plain Chart.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt, make the ſquare A B C D of what length, and breadth you pleaſe, and divide each ſide into as many equall parts as your occaſion requires, and then draw ſtraight lines through theſe parts croſſing one another at right angles, and ſo making many little Geometricall ſquares, each of which you may ſuppoſe to contain one degree, in longitude and latitude,<note n="*" place="margin">According to account 20 Leagues are in one degree, &amp; ſo each 10 part wil be 2 leagus, but it is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, as you may ſee in the third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of this Chapter.</note> Then on the foure ſides of the Chart, let each of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees be ſubdivided into 10 parts, ſo each part wil contain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two leagues, which I therefore call double leagues. And this diviſion of your Chart will be exact enough for the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans uſe, ſo that you need not trouble your ſelf to divide the degrees into 20 parts or 20 leagues, eſpecially becauſe this way of account by decimals or tenth parts, is more eaſie and ready then any other. And if you keepe your account by Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick, you may ſuppoſe each of theſe parts to be ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into 10, ſo every degree will contain 100 parts, which will very well agree with the Chart, better then the old diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by 60 minutes, and is far more exact and eaſie. This ſhort deſcription, if you remember what hath been ſhewed in the firſt and ſecond Chapters, ſhewing you how to draw and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the lines, with the figure it ſelf following, will I hope be very plain, ſo that I need not repeat thoſe things before, but proceed to the uſes of it.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117362:13"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                        <head>The Figure of the <hi>Plain Chart.</hi>
                        </head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117362:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION I.</hi> Knowing the longitude and latitude of a place, to finde out that very point upon the Chart, and ſo to ſet it upon the Chart.</head>
                  <p>THe Longitude of places, is their diſtance Eaſt and Weſt.<note place="margin">What the longitude and latitude of a place is.</note> The latitude of places, is their diſtance North and South. In the Globe, the longitude of places is accounted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways from the Weſt, Eaſtward; ſtill increaſing the number of degrees, untill they come to 360, which is the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the Globe, ſo that you come to the firſt Meridian againe. This account of the Longitude may begin at any place, but Geographers do commonly begin to reckon it from one of the Iſles of the <hi>Azores.</hi> But it is the beſt way for the Seamen, not much to regard this, but to reckon by the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of longitude, or (which is all one) by the difference of the Meridians of the two places. The latitude of places is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kond by their diſtance from the Equinoctial toward either of the Poles, ſo that it never exceeds 90 degrees. If the place lye between the Equinoctiall and the North pole, it is ſaid to have North latitude. If it lye between the Equinoctiall, and the South Pole, it is ſaid to have South latitude. Now though in ſome propoſitions, the Seaman reckons by the difference of latitude, yet in moſt of his accounts and obſervations he doth reckon the latitude of places by their true diſtance from the Equinoctiall North or South.</p>
                  <p>Now for example of the Propoſition.<note place="margin">By the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a place to finde the point thereof upon the Chart.</note> Suppoſe a place to have 5 degrees of Longitude from the firſt meridian Eaſtward and to have five degrees of north latitude, and it is required to finde out the point, where this place muſt be ſet upon the Chart.</p>
                  <p>To perform this you muſt ſuppoſe the line A B in the Chart to be the firſt Meridian, and becauſe the place propoſed is 5 degrees from it to the Eaſtwards, therefore you muſt count 5 degrees from the line A B both in the top and bottome of your Chart, and laying your ruler there, draw the line H E I, then becauſe the place hath 5 degrees of North latitude, you muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117362:14"/> ſuppoſe the lower line A D to be the Equinoctiall line, and ſo accounting 5 degrees upward in both the ſides of the Chart, lay your ruler there, and draw the line F E G. Now mark where theſe two lines do croſſe one another, which is in the point by E, and this is the point where you muſt ſet the place, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to be placed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 2.</hi> The longitudes and latitudes of two places being known, to finde the Rumbe, which you muſt ſteere your courſe upon, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling directly between them.</head>
                  <p>SUppoſe the firſt place to be A, lying under the Equinoctiall, and ſo having no degree of latitude, and likewiſe to be in the firſt Meridian, and ſo to have no degree of longitude. And let the other place be E, which hath 5 degrees of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and 5 degrees of North latitude as before is ſaid, and it is required to find the Rumbe between theſe two places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">By the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of two places, to finde the Rumbe.</note>Firſt, ſet the places A and E upon the Chart, according to their longitudes and latitudes, as is ſhewed before, then laying your ruler by the two places, draw the line A E: this line ſhews the direct way between theſe two places, and if you would know what Rumbe it is, look back to your divided circle, and ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in the center thereof, open the other to the circle of Rumbes, and keeping that diſtance, ſet one foot in the corner A, and with the other draw the arch K L, then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes, in the point where this arch doth croſſe the line A B, which is at K, open the other to L, which is the place where this arch doth croſſe the line A E, and with this diſtance return to your circle, and ſetting one foot of your compaſſes, in the point where the North line doth croſſe the circle of Rumbes, turn the other downward to the circle, the ſame way as it lyes here, and it will point out the fourth Rumbe, which is North-eaſt, and this is the Rumbe you muſt ſail upon, from A to E. In like manner if you would know the Rumbe from E to A, you muſt ſet one foot of your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117362:14"/> compaſſes in the point E, as you did before in the point A, and draw the arch <hi>a b,</hi> &amp; ſo by your circle of Rumbs you ſhall find that the Rumbe from E to A is South-weſt, which is oppoſite to the North-eaſt. And this is a general rule, look what Rumbe you ſayl upon from one place to another, the Rumbe oppoſed to that, will carry you back again.</p>
                  <p>You might have found out the Rumbe likewiſe by the Scale of Rumbes, and ſo you would have found it to be the fourth Rumbe from the Meridian, which muſt be either North-eaſt or North-weſt, South-eaſt, or South-weſt, which of the foure it is, you may know by the ſituation of the places when you are a little verſed therein, but till then the Rumbe will be found beſt by the circle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 3.</hi> Knowing the Longitude and Latitude of two places, to know how farre they are diſtant one from the other.<note place="margin">3. By the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to finde the diſtance.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>LEt the two places be A and E, whoſe longitude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is as aforeſaid, and it is required to know how farre they are aſunder in ſome known meaſure, <hi>viz.</hi> of miles, leagues, degrees and minutes, or degrees and tenths, or hundred parts.</p>
                  <p>It is the common practiſe among Seamen to reckon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of places by leagues, accounting 20 leagues to a degree,<note place="margin">The beſt way to reckon the diſtance is by tenths.</note> and every league to contain about three miles, and ſo each mile to be the 60 part of a degree or one minute. But this way is very troubleſome, and requires often reduction of one ſort of parts to another. The decimall way of account is far more ready and eaſie, and therefore I have divided the degrees on the ſides of the Chart only in to 10 parts which will be exact enough to this purpoſe, each of thoſe parts will contain about two leagues, and therefore I call them double leagues or tenths of a degree. If you deſire to be more exact when you uſe your pen you may ſuppoſe each of theſe to be ſubdivided into 10, and ſo make 100 parts in a degree, &amp; then by adding to a cypher, or taking away the laſt figure, they will be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced one to the other.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117362:15"/>
                  <p>Having thus determined the manner of the meaſure, the way to finde the diſtance of the places is thus Firſt, ſet the places upon the Chart according to their longitude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude at A and E, then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in one of the places as A, open the other to E the other place, then meaſure this diſtance in one of the ſides of your Chart, and your compaſſes wil reach from the corner A to * 7 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,<note place="margin">7, 07.</note> and one of the tenth parts very neer, and that is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the two places, or 71 double leagues or tenth parts, or 710 hundred parts <hi>ferè.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The true quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree upon the earth.</note>And here by the way, give me leave to tell you, that it is not enough for you thus to know the diſtances of places in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and parts, but it is neceſſary alſo to know, the juſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity or meaſure of a degree. And here in the common rule is much out, which accounts 5 foot to a pace, and 1000 ſuch pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that is 5000 feet to a mile, and 60 ſuch miles, that is 300000 feet to a degree. Neither will the Engliſh mile which is ſomewhat more then this ſerve the turne, whoſe length is thus by the Statute. 16 feet and a half make a pole, 40 poles make a furlong, and 8 furlongs, that is 5280 feet, make a mile: and ſo 60 ſuch miles do contain 316800 feet.<note place="margin">See the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Practice</note> But Mr. <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> by meaſuring the way from <hi>Yorke</hi> to <hi>London</hi> found that a degree doth exactly containe 367200 Engliſh feet, and ſhews how this experiment agrees with former experiments made by others, if rightly conſidered: however his experiment is ſo full and punctuall, that it may well paſſe for currant, rather then any others which differ from it.</p>
                  <p>Now by this reckoning, if one degree contain 367200 feet, then the tenth part of a degree doth contain 36720 feet, and the hundreth part of a degree doth contain 3672 feet. Thus you ſhall know the true diſtance of places, knowing how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees and parts they are aſunder.</p>
                  <p>And the knowledge hereof is very conſiderable in the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your dead reckoning by the Log-line,<note place="margin">How your log-line ought to be marked,</note> which you ſhall doe well to rectifie according to this experiment thus. If you keep your account by an half minute glaſſe, then at every 30 feet length of your line, you muſt make a knot: and then ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117362:15"/> many of thoſe knots as you veer out in half a minute, ſo many 100 parts of a degree the ſhip runs in an hour. As if you veer but one knot while the halfe minute glaſſe is running, then the ſhip runs but 1/100, that is one hundreth part of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in an hower, if you veer 2 knots, then the ſhip runs 2/100 parts of a degree, and ſo if you veer 10 of thoſe knots in half a minute, then the ſhip runs 20/100 or one tenth part of a degree in an hour. If the glaſſe be out not juſt at a knot, then for every 3 feet from the laſt knot you may count a tenth part of an hundreth part more.</p>
                  <p>And though by this reckoning there be but 360000 feet, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to a degree, whereas there ſhould be 367200, theſe 7200 feet are thought fit to be abated, not onely in regard of the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundity of the number, to avoid fractions but for theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations. Firſt, becauſe though he that veers the line be never ſo careful not to over-hale it, yet the log will be drawn thereby ſomewhat after the ſhip. Secondly, the Eddy which the ſhip makes, is ſubject to draw the log ſomewhat after it; or at leaſt ſo to dead the water, that it will ſomewhat hinder the motion of the log. Thirdly, the wind and waves beating after the ſhip will drive the log ſomewhat forwarder then it ſhould be. For theſe cauſes, the way of the ſhip may very well be ſomewhat more then the log line ſhews for. Beſides if this were not ſo, yet it is the beſt way to have your reckoning run ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſhip, that ſo you may not fall upon a place before you are aware of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 4.</hi> Knowing the longitude and latitude of the place from whence you came; the Rumbe you have ſailed upon; and how farre you have ſayled there on: to know the longitude and latitude of the place where you are, at that preſent.<note place="margin">4. By the Rumbe and diſtance, to finde the difference of longitude and latitude.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>LEt the place from whence you have ſailed be A, whoſe longitude and latitude ſuppoſe to be as aforeſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>00 deg. let the rumbe upon which you have ſayled be Northeaſt, and let the diſtance which you have ſayled upon this rumbe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117362:16"/> from the place A,<note place="margin">7, 07.</note> be almoſt * 71 double leagues, or tenths of a degree. Now it is required, to know what place you are now in, that is, what longitude and latitude you are come to.</p>
                  <p>To performe this firſt ſet down the place A according to his longitude and latitude, then by your circle or ſcale of Rumbes, draw the line A L E C which is Northeaſt from the point A, then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of your ſcale, which is on the ſides of your chart, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the other almoſt to 71 double leagues, that is to * 7 deg. and one tenth part almoſt,<note place="margin">7, 07.</note> and with this diſtance ſet one foot in the point A, and with the other croſſe the line A L E C in the point E. This croſſe at E is the place where you are now, and if you would know the latitude &amp; longitude of this place, then lay your ruler (or rather a ſmall thred) to the point E, ſo that it may cut the ſcale of degrees, on both ſides the Chart at like parts, as the line F E G doth, which you ſee cuts the ſcale at juſt 5 degrees on each ſide, which ſhews the latitude of the place E to be 5 degrees North from the Equinoctiall. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to finde out the longitude of the place, lay the thred by the point E, and like parts of the ſcale of longitude, both at the top and bottome of the Chart, as the line H E I doth, and it will ſhew that the longitude of the place is juſt 5 degrees. So that the place where you now are which is E, hath 5 deg, of north latitude, and 5 deg. of longitude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Note.</hi> How to keepe your dead reckoning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Chart.</note>This is the way whereby you may beſt keep your dead rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning upon your Chart. For the Seaman alwayes knowes what point of his compaſſe he ſails upon, and alſo by the log-line, or by experience, he may gueſſe very well how far his ſhip goes in an hour, and by that, for any other time, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance being thus ſet upon the Rumbe line in the Chart, ſhews him ſtill whereabouts he is. And it will be very good, at all times to keep this dead reckoning as carefully as you can, yea, though you ſayle neer the meridian, and ſo have no need of it for the preſent, yet then you may the better ſee how your dead reckoning agrees with your obſervations, and ſo gaine expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to keep your dead reckoning more truly, in ſuch cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and againſt ſuch times, as you ſhall have more need of it.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117362:16"/> For ſome times it may be cloſe weather, for 3 or 4 dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and in courſes that lye neer the Eaſt and Weſt, you will be forced to ſticke to your dead reckoning, having no helpe to rectifie it by the obſervation of the latitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 5.</hi> Knowing the longitude and latitude of the place, from whence you ſet ſayl: together with the Rumbe you have ſayled upon; and by obſervation knowing the latitude of the place you are in: to know thereby the longitude of this place, and how farre it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the place you came.</head>
                  <p>LEt the place from whence you ſet ſail be A, whoſe longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude ſuppoſe to be as before; let the Rumbe upon which you have ſailed be North-eaſt; and let the latitude of the place where you are, according to your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation be 5 degrees of North latitude. Now it is required to finde out the longitude of this place, and how it is diſtant from the place at A.<note place="margin">5. By the Rumbe and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to finde the difference of the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and the diſtance.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To performe this, firſt ſet downe the place A in your chart, according to its longitude and latitude, and draw the line A L E C which is the Northeaſt Rumbe from the point A, as is before ſhewed. Then becauſe by your obſervation you finde yourſelfe to be in 5 deg. of North-latitude, count 5 degrees on both the ſides of your Chart, and laying your ruler thereto, draw the line F E G. Now marke well, where this line doth croſſe the line of the Rumbe A L E C, which is in the point E: for this point is the place where you are at the time of this obſervation. Now to know the longitude of this place, lay your ruler or a thred by the croſſe at E, ſo that it may cut like parts of the degrees of longitude, both at the top and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of your Chart, ſo you ſhall draw the line H E I, which ſhews that the longitude of the place is 5 degrees. Laſtly, to finde the diſtance of this place from A, ſet one foot of your compaſſes in A, and open the other to E, and meaſure this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in your ſcale, you ſhall finde it to be 71 double leagues, or 7 deg. one tenth almoſt.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117362:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note>Now this is the moſt certain way that the Seaman can keep his account by, and therefore if there be any difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your dead reckoning and this: you muſt correct your dead reckoning by this, and not this by that. And therefore it concerneth the Seaman to be very carefull in theſe two things, upon which the ground of this Propoſition depends. Firſt, that the ſhip be ſteered exactly upon the Rumbe ſuppoſed, and to this end, not onely the Steers man muſt be carefull to keep the ſhip to the Rumbe of the compaſſe, which he is appointed, but you muſt be carefull to obſerve the variation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe and allow for it. And ſecondly when you make obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the latitude, you muſt do it with true and good large Inſtruments, and uſe the beſt diligence you can in obſerving by them, that ſo you may finde your latitude as exactly as you can.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 6.</hi> How to rectifie your account, when your dead reckoning differs from your account by obſervation.</head>
                  <p>THis Propoſition hath two caſes, the firſt is when yon have kept your way onely upon one point of the compaſſe.<note place="margin">6. How to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</note> The ſecond is when you have been forced to ſayl upon two or more ſeverall points, before you could make any obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the latitude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caſe</hi> 1. If you have ſayled only upon one Rumbe.</note>In the firſt of theſe caſes, if you have onely ſayled upon one point of the compaſſe: as for example, ſuppoſe you have ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the point I which lies under the Equinoctiall line in 5 degrees of Longitude; upon the third Rumbe from the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian <hi>N W by N,</hi> 40 double leagues, or tenths according to your dead reckoning: if you ſet this upon the Chart according to the Rules before ſhewed, according to this your dead rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning you will finde your ſelf to be in the point R, which is in 2 deg. 8/10 of longitude, &amp; in 3 deg. 3/10 of latitude. But at this time ſuppoſe by obſervation, you finde that you are but juſt in 3 degr. of North latitude. Wherefore to finde the true place where you are, do thus.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117362:17"/>
                  <p>Firſt, lay your Ruler, to 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deg. of latitude on both the ſides of your Chart; and draw the line <hi>c</hi> M <hi>d,</hi> and marke where it doth croſſe the line of the Rumbe I R, which is at M, and this is the place where you muſt reckon your ſelfe to be at the time of your obſervation, and not at R, as you ſuppoſed by your dead reckoning. Now if you examine the longitude and latitude of this place M by the former rules, you will find that it lyes in 3 degr. of longitude, and in 5 deg. of north la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and from this place you muſt ſet off your next courſe, and diſtance, and not from R.</p>
                  <p>But now for the ſecond caſe.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caſe</hi> 2. When you have ſailed upon divers Rumbes.</note> If it ſo happen, that you are forced to ſayl upon two or more ſeverall points of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, before you can make an obſervation of the latitude to correct your dead reckoning by. As ſuppoſe you had ſayled according to your dead reckoning, firſt <hi>N W by N,</hi> 40 double leagues, which is ſet down from I to R, (though in truth you had ſailed but from I to M; which is but 36 double leagues) and then being forced to ſhift your courſe to <hi>N E by E,</hi> and ſhould ſail upon this rumbe likewiſe according to your dead reckoning 40 double leagues, and at this inſtant time, you finde by obſervation that you are but in 5 degrees of north latitude: to know the true longitude of this place, you muſt doe thus.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, from the point I, ſet the firſt 40 double leagues upon the Rumbe <hi>N W by N,</hi> which will end at R. Then from the point R draw the rumbe <hi>N E by E,</hi> which is the line R Q, and ſet thereon the 40 double leagues from R to Q: thus you will finde Q to be the place you ſhould be in, according to your dead reckoning which is in 5 d. 5/10 and ſomewhat<note n="*" place="margin">5<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 55.</note> more of north latitude, whereas by your obſervation you finde that you are but in 5 deg. of north latitude: now to know the true place where you are, in reſpect of the longitude, becauſe you have ſayled upon two rumbes, draw the line I Q from I, the firſt place you ſet ſayl from, to Q, the place of your dead re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, and then drawing the line F E G at 5 deg. of latitude according to your obſervation of the latitude; marke where it croſſeth this line I Q, which is in the point N, and this is the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117362:18"/> true place you are in, whoſe longitude is 6 deg. and whoſe latitude is 5 deg. north. In like manner, if you ſhould ſail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 3 or 4 ſeverall Rumbes before you can make an obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Latitude, your beſt way will be to draw a line from the firſt place of your voyage to that preſent place according to your dead reckoning; or at leaſt from the laſt place, where you made a fair obſervation, and are thereby well aſſured both of the longitude and latitude thereof: For otherwiſe you may be much miſtaken in the longitude of your places.</p>
                  <p>As for inſtance, if in the laſt example, you ſhould thinke you were in that place, where the line of latitude F E G doth cut the laſt rumbe you ſayled upon, according to your dead reckoning, <hi>viz.</hi> the line R Q, by this account you would be but in O, which is but in 5 deg. 35/100 of longitude, whereas you ſee by the other way which is the truth, you are in 6 deg. of longitude, ſo that the difference is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>/100. which is very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in ſo ſmall a ſpace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 7.</hi> Being to ſayl from one place to another, but by reaſon of croſſe winds, or the coaſtings of the land, you cannot ſail thither upon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect point of the compaſſe which lies between the two places, but are forced to alter your courſe ſeverall times: yet how you ſhould keep your account of your way, ſo that you may know at any time what longitude and latitude you are in, and how the place you are bound to bears from you, and how farr you want to it.<note place="margin">7. The manner of keeping your reckoning upon the Chart.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">This Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion contains the uſe and practiſe of all the former.</note>FOr example, ſuppoſe you were to ſayle from the place I, in the former Chart, which is under the Equinoctiall, and in 5 degrees of longitude; unto the place H, which hath 5 deg. of longitude, and 10 degrees of north latitude: here the direct way from I to H lies full north: But ſuppoſing that you cannot ſail upon this point, but are forced firſt to run <hi>N W by N</hi> 36 double leagues, and then <hi>N E by E</hi> 36 doubled leagues more, the queſtion is what is the longitude and latitude of this place, and how farre it is diſtant from the place H, and upon what point of the compaſſe it lyes from it.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:117362:18"/>
                  <p>Firſt, from the point I, draw the Rumbe <hi>N W by N,</hi> and ſet off theron 36 double leagues from I to M. Then from this point M draw the Rumbe <hi>N E by E,</hi> and ſet off thereon the 36 dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leagues which you have ſayled upon it, from M to N: thus you ſhall finde, that N is the place wherein you are, whoſe longitude is fix degrees, and whoſe latitude is five degrees. Now if you lay a ruler from this point N, to the place you are bound, to which is H, and draw the line H N, this line is the direct way to the place you are bound, and by the help your circle or ſcale of Rumbes, you ſhall finde that it lyes <hi>North by Weſt,</hi> or the firſt Rumbe from the meridian Weſtward. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, if you ſet one end of your compaſſes in N, and open the other to H, and meaſure that diſtance in the ſides of the Charts, you will finde it to be about 5 degrees 1/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> or 51 dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leagues, and ſo much you want to the end of your voyage.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 8.</hi> How to know the diſtance of any <hi>Cape, Headland,</hi> or <hi>Iſland,</hi> from you, which you can ſee at two diſtant places.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">8. To know the diſtance of any Cape from you</note>SUppoſe that ſayling on the Sea, you eſpie an Iſland or Cape lying at the firſt ſight, juſt <hi>North-eaſt</hi> from you; and then ſayling forward upon your way, which lies full North, to the diſtance of 5 leagues, you then obſerve that the Iſland lies full Eaſt from you, the queſtion is to know the diſtance of this Iſle from either of theſe two places.</p>
                  <p>In ſuch queſtions as this, you may ſuppoſe each degree in the former Chart to ſtand now but for a league,<note place="margin">Theſe two fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions rather belong to the plain table then the chart.</note> and let the firſt place where you eſpied the Iſland be at A, now becauſe the Iſland lay <hi>North-eaſt,</hi> from this place, draw the line A B which is <hi>N E</hi> from A. Then count the 5 leagues which you have ſayled upon your courſe which was full north, in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian line from A to F, and becauſe from this place, the Iſland did lye ful Eaſt, therefore from this point F, draw the Eaſt line F E G, and marke where this line, doth croſſe the former line A E of <hi>N E</hi> from A, which is in the point E. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt needs be the place of the Iſland, whoſe diſtance if
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117362:19"/> you take with your compaſſes, and meaſure in the ſides of the Chart, you ſhall finde that the place E is diſtant from A 7 leagues and almoſt 1/15 part of a league; and from F juſt 5 leagues.<note n="*" place="margin">A double uſe of this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> And by this means if you know the longitude and latitude of this Iſle or Cape, you may the more certainly know the truth of your account, and if need be correct it. Or if you knew not the place before, you may ſet it down in your chart by its longitude and latitude which you finde it to be in, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the beſt account you can make by your obſervation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 9.</hi> By obſerving upon what Rumbes many places lye from you at two ſeverall ſtations; to finde the diſtances of thoſe places, and their true poſture and bearing one from another.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">9. To finde out the true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and bearing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places. The uſe of this Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>AS in the former Propoſition you did for one place, ſo in this you may do for many. And this will be of good uſe, for hereby, ſayling in ſight of any Coaſt, you may finde out how the Points and Rivers and ſuch like lye, and ſo make a Map thereof. The way to perform which is thus. Firſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve well how the ſeverall places lie from your firſt ſtation, which ſuppoſe to be A; and let theſe three places be obſerved by you <hi>viz.</hi> I M and E I bears from A full Eaſt, M and E, North-eaſt, therefore draw the lines A I and A M E according to the bearing of the places from A. Secondly, you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your courſe which you ſail upon, untill you come to the ſecond ſtation, which ſuppoſe to be five leagues full North, let this be ſet down according to its place at F. Thirdly, this being your ſecond ſtation, obſerve how the three-former places bear from this place, and ſuppoſe you find, that E lyes full eaſt from this place, M lyes South-eaſt by eaſt, and I lyes South-eaſt, from this ſecond ſtation. Then draw theſe lines F E, F M, F I, from the point F, and mark well where they croſſe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer lines, which will be in the ſaid points E M and I, and thus theſe three places E M I are ſet down according to their true poſitions and diſtances, both from the two ſtations A and F, and likewiſe one from another, ſo that if you try by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117362:19"/> rules, and your comaſſes you ſhall finde M lyes from I, <hi>N W b N</hi> 3 leagues and 6/10, and E lyes from M, <hi>N E,</hi> 2 leagues and 8/10. Thus you may eaſily deſcribe the coaſt of a Country as you ſayle by it in ſight of it, which will be both pleaſant and profitable, eſpecially when you light upon Coaſts that have not been diſcovered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 10.</hi> To draw a Rumbe line from any point aſſigned.</head>
                  <p>IN this deſcription of the plain Chart, I have purpoſely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the old cuſtome,<note place="margin">10. To draw a Rumbe line from any point in the Chart.</note> of peſtering the Chart with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Rumbe lines, to little or no purpoſe. For though they may ſeeme to be of ſome uſe in this Propoſition; yet it may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be performed, onely by the lines of longitude and latitude with the help of the circle, or ſcale of Rumbes. For firſt, if your point aſſigned fall out in any of the meridian lines, then you may readily by the rules of the ſecond chapter, <hi>pag.</hi> 13, 14. draw any rumbe line from that point. But if your point do not fall juſt upon, a meridian line, then you muſt, firſt, from the point aſſigned, draw a line parallel to any one of the meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an lines, as is ſhewed by the ſecond propoſition of the firſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, and then draw the Rumbe line from your point aſſigned in that line, as you did before. Thus you ſee theſe lines of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude and latitude are of double uſe. For firſt, they readily ſhew you the longitude and latitude of any place in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by the eye. And then they help in the drawing rumbe lines, from any point. Whereas to draw ſo many rumbes after the uſuall manner, is but a ſpending much time and labour to little purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:117362:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Shewing how to make a Sea-chart for any part of the World, which ſhall agree in all particulars with the Globe; with ſeverall Propoſitions ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner of uſing it.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The defects of the plain Chart.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He way of ſayling by the plain chart, is very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to underſtand, as you may ſee by what hath been ſaid in the former chapter: But it hath this inconvenience, that it is fit to be uſed onely in places neer the Equinoctiall, or in ſome ſhort voyages. For it ſuppoſeth the degrees of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude to be all of one length, in every Latitude, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it makes the degrees both of longitude and latitude, all of one length and breadth in all places. But you muſt know that though the degrees of Latitude, are alwayes of one and the ſame breadth (<hi>viz.</hi> about twenty leagues) yet the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of longitude are not all of this length, but as you may ſee in the Globe, they grow leſſe and leſſe toward the Poles: ſo that though about the Equinoctiall, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of longitude is equall to a degree of latitude, <hi>viz.</hi> about 20 leagues: yet in the latitude of 60 deg. one degree of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is equall, but to half a degree of latitude, <hi>viz.</hi> about 10 leagues; and about the latitude of 75 deg. 30′, one degree of longitude is equall but to a quarter of a degree of latitude, which is about 5 leagues. And therefore it is impoſſible to ſet three places upon the plain chart, which differ much in longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude, as they ought to be placed, that is according to their places on the Globe. But if you ſet them down, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their longitudes and latitudes; then they will not ſtand in their true Rumbes and Diſtances one from the other: and if you ſtrive to ſet them down according to their Rumbes and Diſtances; then their Longitudes and Latitudes will not fail out right.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:117362:20"/>
               <p>And therefore though you may make a ſhift to performe ſome ſhort voyages by it, yet you cannot uſe it in any long voyage without great errour: except you onely goe from one place to another, and ſo directly back again to the ſame place, from whence you came, and by the ſame courſe which you came.<note n="*" place="margin">This example is M. <hi>Norwoods</hi> in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes of ſayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> For example, ſuppoſe you were to ſail from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> to the <hi>Summer Iſlands,</hi> and ſhould according to the common courſe firſt ſail <hi>South-weſt,</hi> about 500 leagues, and then fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your ſelf to be in the latitude of 32 deg. 20′, you ſhould then ſail full <hi>Weſt</hi> 782 leagues, and then you ſhould finde your ſelfe directly South from the <hi>Summer Ilands,</hi> and about 2 leagues off them. Now by this reckoning upon the plain chart, theſe Iſlands ſhould be diſtant from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> 1189 leagues. Now admitting this reckoning outward to be true, and theſe places to be thus ſcituated upon the plain chart, let us ſuppoſe the reckoning homewards to be alſo kept upon the plain chart. And becauſe in comming home, men keep to the Northwards, ſuppoſe that you ſteer away firſt <hi>N E</hi> half a point Eaſterly 200 leagues; then <hi>N E by E</hi> 100 leagues, next <hi>E N E</hi> half a point northerly 165 leagues; then <hi>E N E</hi> 130 leagues; then <hi>E N E</hi> halfe a point Eaſterly 88 leagues, then <hi>E by N</hi> 70 leagues; laſtly, <hi>Eaſt</hi> 317 leagues; if you ſet down this reckoning upon the plain chart, you will be yet ſhort of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> about 160 leagues, whereas you are already come unto the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and ſo you will finde it, if you keep your rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning by this following Sea-chart.</p>
               <p>For the reformation hereof, Mr. <hi>Wright</hi> in his book of the <hi>Errours of Navigation,</hi> hath ſhewed how to make, and hath alſo made a table, by the continuall addition of the ſecants of every minute, which ſhews how much you are to lengthen the degrees of latitude in your Map, that ſo there may be a true proportion between the degrees of Longitude and Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in all places: which table Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi> hath abridged, and made it more plain and eaſie, by reducing it into decimall parts. I ſhall here ſhew you how to do the ſame by <hi>Geometry,</hi> and how to make a line of Latitudes, or a Meridian line an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to any line of longitudes.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:117362:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:117362:21"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The projecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Line.</note>Firſt, make the Quadrants A B C of what largnes you pleaſe, and divide the limbe thereof into 90 degrees numbring them from B towards C, then divide the ſide of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant A B into 10 equall parts, and draw ſtraight lines from them parallel to A C, then take one of theſe parts from A to E, and ſubdivide it into 10 leſſer parts, and draw lines from them parallel unto A C. Now you muſt note that the length of this one part A C is to be your radius, or the meaſure of one degree of longitude in your Chart, ſo that the whole line A B will be 10 degrees, and becauſe theſe degrees of longitude are to be of one length in all latitudes, therefore the degrees of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude muſt increaſe as the ſecants of the latitudes increaſe. Therefore if you would know how long one degree of latitude muſt be in the latitude of 30 deg. lay your ruler to the center A, and the arch of the quadrant at 30 deg. and draw the line A G, now the radius being A E, this line A G is the ſecant of 30 deg. to that radius, and muſt be the length of one degree of latitude in a Chart for that latitude. So likewiſe the line A H which is the ſecant of 45 deg. to that radius, muſt be the length of one degree of latitude, in the latitude of 45 deg. and ſo for any other latitude: and note that the 10 intermedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate lines may ſerve to divide each of theſe degrees into 10 parts.</p>
               <p>If you would examine the truth of this projection how it agrees with the Globe;<note place="margin">The proof of of this proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> whereas in the Globe one degree of latitude is equall to two degrees of longitude in the latitude of 60 deg: ſo here A K the ſecant of 60 deg. is twice the length of A E the meaſure of one degree of longitude, and whereas in the Globe one degree of latitude is equall to foure degrees of longitude in the latitude of 75 deg. 30′: ſo here A L the ſecant of 75 deg. 30′ is four times the length of A E, and ſo the proportion will hold in any other latitude.</p>
               <p>If you deſire to make a table hereof,<note place="margin">To make a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian line.</note> then you may make the whole line A B to be your radius, or the length of one degree, which you may divide into 100 parts, and then the ſecants will be the lines drawn from the center A to the line B D, thus then the line A I will be the ſecant of 30 degrees,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117362:22"/> whoſe length is 115, as you may meaſure in the ſcale A B if it were increaſed. And ſo the line A D is the ſecant of 45 degr. whoſe length is 141.<note place="margin">Note.</note> * And note here if you make the table for whole degrees only, then it wil be the beſt way to draw the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant line through the midſt of the degree, as if you would know the length of the line which muſt reach from 29 degrees to 30 degrees, draw the line through 29 degrees 30 minutes, the length wherof will be 115, and ſo by the continuall addition of theſe Secants you may make the Table following, which you ſhall finde agrees very well with Maſter <hi>Gunters,</hi> only his radius is divided into 1000 parts and this but into 100.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Another way to make a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian line.</note>Alſo by the Quadrant, or the Table, you may make the two Meridian lines following. But if you make them by the Quadrant, then becauſe the degrees would fall too cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if they were all drawn, under the firſt Radius A E, you may remove the Radius A E further from the center, and then draw them under it. As for example, the diſtance between the lines 8 and 9 being equall to the diſtance A E, you may there draw the firſt 20 degrees. Then between the lines 7 and 8 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the like diſtance, draw the next ten degrees which is to 30, and ſo do the reſt as you ſee in the Quadrant. Then taking out theſe degrees one by one with your compaſſes, ſet them upon the Meridian line, of your Chart, or make a Meridian line, at your leaſure, as in the following figure, which will be very ready upon any occaſion.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117362:22"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A Table of the Meridian line, as it is taken out of the <hi>Quadrant,</hi> as aforeſaid, the <hi>Radius</hi> or the whole line A B being divided into 100 parts.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Lati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">The Meridi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an line</cell>
                        <cell role="label">The Sec to be ad.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">D.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">D.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">P.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>01</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>02</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>03</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>04</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>05</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>07</cell>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>103</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>103</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>104</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>104</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>106</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>106</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>107</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>107</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>108</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>109</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>94</cell>
                        <cell>111</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>06</cell>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>113</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>113</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>115</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>116</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>117</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>119</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>121</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>123</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>125</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>126</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>128</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>129</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>02</cell>
                        <cell>131</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>134</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>136</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>138</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                        <cell>143</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>145</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                        <cell>148</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>151</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                        <cell>154</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>157</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>161</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>164</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>168</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>172</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>177</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>181</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>186</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>197</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>77</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>203</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>209</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>217</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>224</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>232</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>241</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>251</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>262</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>96</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>273</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>285</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>315</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>108</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                        <cell>333</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>352</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>116</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>374</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>399</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>77</cell>
                        <cell>124</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>427</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>78</cell>
                        <cell>129</cell>
                        <cell>07</cell>
                        <cell>462</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                        <cell>134</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>502</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>139</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>549</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>145</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>607</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>677</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>768</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>84</cell>
                        <cell>168</cell>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>885</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>179</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>1040</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>1280</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>87</cell>
                        <cell>208</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>1649</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>231</cell>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>2325</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>89</cell>
                        <cell>271</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>3985</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">infinite</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:117362:23"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>The leſſer <hi>Meridian Line,</hi> for generall <hi>Maps.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head>The long <hi>Meridian Line,</hi> for particular <hi>Maps.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117362:23"/>
               <p>I have made here two meridian lines and that for two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, becauſe in the larger line after 80 degrees of lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the degrees grew ſo large, and increaſed ſo much, that it would be both needleſſe and troubleſome to make any uſe of them: but the chief reaſon is this. Becauſe when you are to goe any long voyage, it wil be needfull for you firſt to make a generall Map of your whole voyage by the leſſer line, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may know the courſe and diſtance thereof in generall: and then to make three or four other charts by the greater line upon which, with your ruler and compaſſes you may ſet down your dayly courſes and diſtances more exactly.</p>
               <p>Alſo I have made theſe two lines in ſuch proportion, that the one is the tenth part of the other, that ſo that they may both agree with the ſcale upon the Quadrant.</p>
               <p>Now the way to make one of theſe charts is very eaſie,<note place="margin">To make a Sea Chart by theſe Meridian lines.</note> and much after the manner of the plain chart. For firſt, you may draw the line of Eaſt and Weſt A B of what length you pleaſe, and divide it into equall parts or degrees, then you may erect a perpendicular line either at one of the ends of the line or in any of the diviſions toward the midſt of the line, and then draw the other parallels of longitude parallel thereto, ſo far it is all one with the plain chart, but when you come to draw the parallels of latitude, you muſt not make them all equall, (though they muſt be all parallel) each to other; but you muſt either with your compaſſes, take them out of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, or which is more eaſie, lay a ſcroule of paper to the Meridian line which is ready drawn to your hand, and ſo mark out the degrees of latitude upon the ſcroule of paper, and then laying that ſcroule to the ſides of your chart, you may tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the degrees of latitude into the ſides of your chart, and through them draw the parallels, and ſet fit numbers to them, as in the figure.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117362:24"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>The figure of a generall Sea-Chart, containing almoſt an eighth part of the Globe. <hi>NORTH.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:117362:24"/>
               <p>Now though this be not a general chart of the whole globe, yet it may be called a generall chart in reſpect of others, which wil ſerve onely for a leſſer portion of the Globe. For this chart containeth almoſt an eighth part of the Globe, and may be fitted to ſet forth any part thereof. For if you change the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the longitude, if the latitude be northward, it wil ſerve as it now ſtands: but if the latitude be Southward, you muſt turne the bottome upward. If you have occaſion in one chart, to ſet down both North and South latitude: then you muſt draw the like parallels of latitude below the Equinoctial, as theſe are above it.</p>
               <p>Now I wil ſhew you how the ſeveral Propoſitions which were performed by the plain chart, may be performed by this, and wherein they agree, and wherein they differ.</p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 1.</hi> Knowing the longitude and latitude of any place, to ſet it upon the Chart.<note place="margin">1. By the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tede, to finde the point of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place in the Chart.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis muſt be done, as in the plain chart. For firſt laying your ruler by the longitude of the place, you muſt draw a little occult line as neere the latitude of the place as you can gueſs, then laying your ruler to the latitude of the place croſſe that line you drew before with another little line, and ſo the croſſing of theſe two lines wil ſhew you the point where the place muſt be ſuppoſed to ſtand.<note place="margin">Example.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus ſuppoſing the longitude of the <hi>Summer Ilands</hi> to be 300 degrees, and the latitude thereof 32 degrees, 25 minutes, you wil finde that it muſt be ſet at S, upon the chart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 2.</hi> The longitudes and latitudes of two places being known, to finde the rumbe which you muſt ſaile upon, to go directly from the one place to the other.<note place="margin">2. By the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of two places to finde the Rumbe. <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>SUppoſe the one place to be the <hi>Summer Ilands,</hi> whoſe longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude we wil ſuppoſe to be as is before ſet down,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117362:25"/> let the other place be the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> whoſe latitude is about 50 deg. and let the longitude thereof be ſuppoſed to be 10 degr. ſo the difference of the longitude of the two places, wil be 70 deg. (as Mr. <hi>Norwood</hi> both in his book of the <hi>Doctrine of Triangles,</hi> and his <hi>Seamans Practice</hi> ſuppoſeth them to be, though as he ſaith in one place, he doth not think them to be ſo far diſtant) and it is required to finde the rumbe.</p>
                  <p>This Propoſition muſt alſo be performed as in the plain chart. For firſt, the two places muſt be ſet upon the chart, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their longitudes and latitudes, which will be at S and L, then draw a ſtrait line from S to L, this repreſents the direct way between the two places, now to know what rumbe this is, open your compaſſes to the Radius of your ſcale of rumbes, and ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in S with the other, draw the arch R M, then ſetting one foot of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes in R, open the other to the croſſing of the line, and the arch at M, and meaſuring that diſtance on your ſcale of chords or Rumbes, ſo ſhall you finde it to be 71 deg. 21 min. or the ſixt rumbe and ſomewhat above a quarter of a rumbe, from the Meridian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 3.</hi> Knowing the longitudes and latitudes of two places to know how farre they are diſtant one from another.<note place="margin">3. To meaſure the diſtance of places.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>LEt the two places be as is before ſaid S and L, it is required to finde their diſtance.</p>
                  <p>In the working this Propoſition, there is ſome difference from the plain chart, for whereas there you meaſure the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of places by one and the ſame ſcale of equall parts here you will have uſe of many ſcales, according to the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi>'s way.</note>Now the ordinary way preſcribed by Mr. <hi>Gunter,</hi> to perform this is thus. Open your compaſſes to the diſtance of the two places; and then ſetting your compaſſes in the Meridian line, ſo that the one point of the compaſſes may ſtand juſt ſo much above the greater latitude, as the other doth below the leſſer latitude, and ſo the degrees between them is the diſtance: this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117362:25"/> way may ſerve for ſmall diſtances as Maſter <hi>Gunter</hi> uſeth it; but in greater diſtances it wil not always hold true; and beſides, it is ſomewhat troubleſome to ſet the compaſſes juſt as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the one latitude, as below the other.</p>
                  <p>As in this example, if you take the diſtance S L in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, and meaſure it ſo in the Meridian line, it wil reach from about 16 degrees, to about 66 degree and an halfe, that is 16 degrees and an half above 50 degrees, the greater latitude, and 16 degrees and an halfe below 32 degrees, 25 minutes, the leſſer latitude, and ſo the degrees intercepted between the points of the compaſſes are about 50 degrees and a half, whereas the diſtance of the two places is almoſt 55 degrees.</p>
                  <p>But you ſhall finde the diſtance more exactly,<note place="margin">The way to meaſure the diſtances of places which differ in longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> if you doe thus. Firſt, divide the ſpace that is in the meridian line be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two latitudes into two equall parts, which in this Example will fall at 42 degrees, then take with your compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes halfe the length of the line L S, which is L M, and ſetting one foot of the compaſſes in 42 degrees, which is the middle point between the two latitudes, you ſhall finde that the other point will reach down to 8 degrees and a halfe, then keeping the one foot ſtill fixed in 42 degrees, turne the other foot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and it will reach to 63 degrees and a half; now the degrees of the meridian line between theſe two points are 55, which is the diſtance deſired, which is 550 double leagues or tenths of a degree, or 1100 leagues. But if this diſtance were to be meaſured in the plain chart, the two places being ſet down therein according to their longitudes and latitudes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, their diſtance would be above 72 degrees, which is 340 leagues, more then the truth.</p>
                  <p>If you would meaſure a parallel diſtance,<note place="margin">How to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of places which differ only in longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> as ſuppoſe the two places were L and T, both in the latitude of 50 degrees, and their difference of Longitude is 70, the way will be to take halfe the diſtance which is L Q, with your compaſſes, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one foot in 50 degrees of the meridian line, the other foot will reach to 22 degrees and a half downwards, and to 67 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and a half upward, and if you count the degrees between
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117362:26"/> theſe two places, or elſe ſubſtract the leſſer from the greater, you ſhall finde 45 deg. which is the diſtance of the two places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Another way to meaſure the diſtances of parallel places</note>Yet this may more readily be performed by the Quadrant, <hi>Page</hi> 22, whereby the meridian line was made.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, if you would meaſure a parallel diſtance, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuppoſe you would meaſure the diſtance of the two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces T and L, being both in the latitude of 50 degrees, and their difference of longitude is 70 degrees. Firſt, draw the line A P at 50 degrees in the quadrant, then take the diſtance of the two places T L with your compaſſes, and ſetting one foot in A, the center of the quadrant, with the other foot, croſſe the line A P 50 at P, which is juſt in the midſt between the fourth and fift parallel lines, which are drawn from the ſcale of the quadrant, now becauſe the chart is of the leaſt ſize, therefore you muſt account every of thoſe greater parts, for 10 degrees, and ſo the diſtance will be found to be 45 degrees, as before.</p>
                  <p>Now to know this exactly, theſe greater parts ſhould each of them be divided with lines into ten parts, as the firſt of them is: or elſe you may make uſe of thoſe lines in the firſt part thus. Having made the mark at P, as before; and ſeeing it doth not fall juſt upon one of the parallel lines you may ſet one foot of your compaſſes on the next parallel line at R, and turning the other towards the center A, it will reach in the line P A to the middle line among the leſſer diagonal lines, which ſhews it lacks 5 degrees of 50, and ſo it is 45 degrees.</p>
                  <p>But if you would meaſure the diſtance of two places which differ both in latitude and longitude,<note place="margin">To meaſure the diſtance of places which differ in lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</note> as the two places L and S in the chart, you muſt do thus Firſt, draw the line AM in the quadrant, <hi>pag.</hi> 32, by the arch of the one latitude 32 degrees 25 minutes, then draw the line A P 50, by the arch of the other latitude, 50 degrees, then in any of the parallel lines, divide the ſpace between theſe two lines A M and A P 50 into two equal parts, which if you do in the eighth parallel, the halfe or midſt wil be at N,, then draw the line A N, which wil be your ſcale to meaſure this diſtance by. Now if you take the diſtance S L in the chart, and ſet it on the line A N in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117362:26"/> quadrant, it will reach from A to S, that is in the midſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the fift and ſixt parallel lines, ſo that the diſtance is 55 degrees, for every one of theſe parallel lines ſtands for 10 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees when the chart is drawn by the little meridian line.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 4.</hi> Knowing the longitude and latitude of the place from whence you came, and the rumbe you have ſayled upon, and how farre you have ſailed on that rumbe: to know the longitude and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the place you are in.<note place="margin">4. By the rumbe and diſtance, to finde the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The way of keeping your dead recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon the Sea-Chart.</note>THis Propoſition ſhews the way how you muſt keep your dead reckoning upon your chart, which is good to be done always, but eſpecially when you cannot have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to obſerve the latitudes, or when your courſe lies neer the Eaſt or Weſt, ſo that obſervation of the latitude will do you little or no good, in keeping of your account of the way you have ſailed. And that you may the more exactly keep this account, it wil be needful to make your chart by the greater meridian line, and if your voyage be ſo long that one ſheet of paper wil not make a chart big enough, you may put it into two or three ſheets, and keeping your daily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts upon them, you may as often as you ſhall ſee cauſe, transfer your accounts out of theſe perticularr charts, into your general chart, and ſo you ſhal ſee the better how to direct your courſe in general.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſuppoſing the voyage to be as is before mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the <hi>Summer Ilands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Example.</note> the chart follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn by the greater meridian line may contain a part of that voyage. And though this chart being ſtraitned for room contain but a very little part of the voyage, yet a ſheet of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per wil contain one third part of the whole voyage, and it would be very ready and neceſſary for the Seamans uſe, if ſuch blank charts were drawn to all latitudes, which might be done to 70 or 80 degrees in 4 or 5 ſheets of paper ſo that by ſetting, fitting numbers of longitude to them, you might make them ſerve for moſt places in the whole World.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117362:27"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:117362:27"/>
                  <p>Having provided the blank chart, let the example to explain the Propoſition be this. <hi>Having ſayled from the Lizard, about the diſtance of</hi> 5 <hi>degrees, or</hi> 50 <hi>tenths on the fift Rumbe from the Meridian S W b W. I would know what longitude and latitude I am come into.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now to perform this, firſt you muſt ſet the <hi>Lizard</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its longitude and latitude aforeſaid upon the chart at L,<note place="margin">Latitude 50<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Longitude 10<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                     </note> then from L draw the line L M which is the rumbe you have ſailed upon, then take five degrees which is the diſtance you have ſailed, out of the meridian line; upon the ſide of your chart from 50 to 45, and ſet it from L to N, ſo the croſſe at N ſhal repreſent the place where you are, which you may readily ſee by the Map, to be about 47 degrees and 2/10 of lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and about 3 degrees 8/10 of longitude, that is 6 degrees 2/10 of longitude, diſtant from the Meridian of L. But if you ſhould keep your account by the plain chart you would reckon your ſelfe but 4 degrees, 2/10 of Longitude diſtant from the place L.</p>
                  <p>And though this way there may be ſome ſmal miſtake, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in over, ſometimes in under reckoning, if you be not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry careful to take your diſtance out of the meridian line, as neer the latitudes as you can, yet if the diſtance be not great, and eſpecially if the Rumbe be not far from the Meridian, your errour wil not be much. And you may the leſſe regard it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this being but your dead reckoning, you need not truſt to it, but may correct it afterward, when you have opportunity to obſerve the latitude.</p>
                  <p>But when your courſe lies neer the Eaſt and Weſt,<note place="margin">Example of a parallel courſe.</note> ſo that you are forced to truſt to your dead reckoning, becauſe you cannot correct it by obſervation of the latitude, then it wil be the more needful, for you to be the more exact in ſetting off your diſtance, which you may doe by the Quadrant: as for example, ſuppoſe you have ſayled the diſtance of 5 degrees, or 50 tenthsful Weſt from L, and would know what longitude you are then in.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, draw the line A R O in the Quadrant <hi>pag.</hi> 32, by the arch of 50 deg, which is the parallel latitude you have ſailed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117362:28"/> in; then becauſe you have ſailed the diſtance of 5 degrees in this latitude, marke where the fifth parallel line in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, croſſeth the line A R O, which is at R, therefore take the diſtance A R out of the Quadrant, and transferre it into the chart from L to R, ſo ſhall R be the true point where you are, whoſe longitude you may ſee by the map to be about 2 degrees 2/10 being diſtant from the Meridian of L 7 degrees 8/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, whereas by the plain chart you would think your ſelf to be but 5 degrees diſtant.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 5.</hi> Knowing the longitude and latitude of the place from whence you ſet ſail, together with the rumbe you have ſayled upon, and by obſervation knowing the latitude of the place you are in: to know thereby the longitude of this place you are in, and how farre you are diſtant from the place you came.<note place="margin">5. By the Rumbe and difference of latitude to finde the point where you are.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis Propoſition is the ſame with the fift propoſition in the uſe of the plain chart, and is performed juſt after the ſame manner, but with far more truth in reſpect of the longitude or difference of meridians. For example, let the place from which you ſet ſail be the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> whoſe longitude and latitude is before ſet down, let the Rumbe upon which you have ſailed be the fifth Rumbe from the meridian S <hi>W by W.</hi> and laſtly, by your obſervation, you finde your ſelf in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of 45 degrees, the longitude and diſtance of this place from L is required.</p>
                  <p>To performe this. Firſt, having made the foregoing chart, ſet down the <hi>Lyzard</hi> according to 'its longitude and latitude at L, then draw the line L M which is the fift Rumbe from the meridian, and laſtly, becauſe you finde your ſelfe to be in the latitude of 45 degrees, lay your ruler to the parallel of 45 in your chart, and draw the line D M. Now the point where this line D M croſſeth the rumbe line L M, is the place which you are then in, whoſe longitude you ſee by the Map is 358 degrees 9/10: ſo that it differs from the meridian of L 11 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 1/10. But if you ſhould performe this propoſition upon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117362:28"/> the plain chart, you would account your ſelf to be but 7 deg. and an half from the meridian of L.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, if you meaſure the length of the line L M, either by the meridian line on the ſide of the chart, or rather by the Quadrant, as was ſhewed before, you will finde that you have ſayled from L; 9 degrees, or 90 tenth.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee this, which is the moſt uſeful propoſition of all, being the moſt certain way by which the Seaman can keep his account, is as ready performed, and juſt in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as in the plain chart. Neither ſhal the Seaman need to trouble himſelf, in keeping his accounts with more curious calculations: for conſidering he cannot obſerve the latitude ſo exactly but that he may miſſe therein 5 or 6 minutes: as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the ſhip cannot be ſteered, ſo exactly, but that it may alter from the Rumbe ſuppoſed, many minutes, if not ſome few degrees: and ſeeing alſo, it will be eaſie to draw the lines of Rumbs and Latitudes, in a chart whoſe meridian line ſhall be about this ſize, more exactly then can be obſerved or ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. What profit will be gained then by more curious calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROPOSITION 6.</hi> The rectifying of your dead reckoning, by your obſervation.<note place="margin">6. </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis Propoſition is to be performed here, as is ſhewed in the plain chart, onely you muſt meaſure your diſtances by the meridian line, neer the latitude you are in.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROPOSITION 7.<note place="margin">7. </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis Propoſition is but for variety, and recollection of what was ſaid before, and to be performed in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner upon this Chart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROPOSITION 8 &amp; 9.<note place="margin">8 &amp; 9.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THeſe two Propoſitions belong onely to the plain chart or plain table, and is not ſo fit for this.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:117362:29"/>
                  <p>In all theſe Propoſitions, there are theſe four principall things to be taken notice of. 1 the Longitude, 2 the Latitude, 3 the Diſtance, 4 the Rumbe. Any two of theſe being known; the other two may be known thereby. So that theſe Propoſitions might be varied many wayes, as you may ſee in Mr. <hi>Gunters</hi> Workes. But what I have ſaid already, being I hope ſufficient to inſtruct you in the nature and uſe of the Chart, and theſe being the moſt neceſſary, I ſhal not further enlarge upon this in this place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of ſayling by a great Circle.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The praiſe of this way of ſayling by a great Circle</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Now come to ſhew how you may ſail by the arch of a great Circle, which is the moſt exact way of ſayling of all others, but in regard of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie that there is in the calculation thereof, it hath diſcouraged the Sea-man from looking after it: but I ſhall ſhevv you hovv this may plainly and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be performed by <hi>Geometry,</hi> vvhich I hope vvil be for the generall profit and eaſe of Seamen. For you muſt knovv that the diſtances of places found out as vvas before ſhevved in the uſe of the Sea-chart,<note place="margin">Firſt, it is the neereſt way.</note> is ſeldome the neereſt diſtance betvveen any tvvo places, but it is onely their diſtance in the rumbe. So that if the tvvo places are not both under the Equinoctiall or both in one meridian, then there is ſomewhat a neerer cut betvven the tvvo places, then the rumbe points out: vvhich ſometimes, eſpecially neere the Poles, is very conſiderable.</p>
               <p>But this is not all the benefit vvhich comes by this vvay of ſayling,<note place="margin">Secondly, it is the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient way.</note> but many times vvhen your courſe lies neer the Eaſt and Weſt, this vvay is farre more convenient. For if you ſhould ſail full Eaſt or Weſt, you muſt altogether depend upon your dead reckoning, having no vvay to help your ſelf, by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the latitude, but novv if you ſail by the arch of a great circle, betvveen tvvo ſuch places, you not onely go the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117362:29"/> neerer vvay, but alſo may alter your latitude many degrees, vvhereby your account may be often rectified,<note n="*" place="margin">So in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>Summer</hi> Ilands the diſtance by the rumbe is 3299 miles. The diſtance by the arch is 3204 miles, that is 95 miles leſſe.</note> as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuppoſe you vvere to ſail from <hi>Spain</hi> to <hi>Virginia,</hi> both vvhich lye neer the parallel of 40 degrees, and ſuppoſe the difference of longitude betvveen tvvo ſuch places in the parallel of 40, to be 70 degrees, the diſtance of theſe tvvo places meaſured in the parallel of 40 (vvhich is the rumbe that leads betvveen the tvvo places being Eaſt and Weſt) is 53 degrees 62/100, but their diſtance in the arch of a great circle is but 52 degrees, 08/100, that is 1 degree, 54/100 leſs. But this as ſaid, is but the leaſt part of the benefit that comes by this vvay of ſayling: the chiefeſt is this, that in ſayling between two ſuch places by the arch of a great circle, you wil firſt in the one half of the way raiſe the Pole 5 degrees 69/100, and then in the other half depreſs the Pole as much, ſo that in your whole Voyage you wil alter the latitude 11 degrees 38/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, &amp; ſo by the obſervation of the latitude you may rectifie your dead recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning very wel, which you cannot do, ſayling in the parallel. Thus you ſee this way of ſayling is not only the neereſt but the beſt way.</p>
               <p>Now concerning this way of ſayling, there hath been but little written by any,<note place="margin">Few have written of this ſubject.</note> and therefore I ſhal be the more large in this. Captain <hi>Saltonſtall</hi> in his Booke called the <hi>Navigator,</hi> hath ſaid ſomwhat how to direct a parallel courſe, but for any other courſe he hath ſaid nothing, and what hee ſheweth is to be performed by Arithmetick. Maſter <hi>Norwood</hi> in his Book of <hi>Trigonometry,</hi> hath added as an appendix many Problemes of Sayling by the arch of a great circle whereby thoſe; who both can, and wil take the pains, may by calculation finde out all things neceſſary in this way of Sayling. But thoſe ways of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation as they are very difficult to the unlearned, ſo they are tedious to thoſe that have the beſt skil: and therefore I hope it will be wel accepted, if I here ſhew you how the ſame may be performed by <hi>Geometry,</hi> both plainly and ſpeedily, and yet with as much exactneſſe, as need be required.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:117362:30"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The chiefe things to be known.</note>And in the purſuance hereof, I ſhal keep as cloſe to Maſter <hi>Norwood,</hi> as I can, both in his Propoſitions and Examples, that thereby you may ſee how neerly my plain lines wil approach to the exactneſſe of his calculations. Now if you obſerve him, there are theſe three things, which muſt be found out in every Example. Firſt, the diſtance of the two places in the arch of a great Circle. Secondly, the angle of poſition from the one place to the other. Thirdly, to finde out what longitudes and latitudes the arch of the great circle doth paſſe through be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two places.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To finde the diſtance of two places.</note>For the firſt of theſe, knowing the longitude and latitude of two places, to finde their diſtance in the arch of a great cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which is always the neereſt diſtance. I might ſhew you how to perform this in the firſt place, but I here paſſe it by for theſe reaſons. Firſt, becauſe Maſter <hi>Wright,</hi> Maſter <hi>Blundevile,</hi> and Captain <hi>Saltonſtall,</hi> have all of them demonſtrated it in their Books already. And ſecondly, becauſe the chief benefit in this way of ſailing doth not ſo much conſiſt in ſaving of a litle way, as in ſayling the moſt convenient way: that is, ſo as you may alter your latitude moſt, and ſo your reckoning may be the more certain. For though neer the Poles, the difference of the diſtance of two places, in the arch of a great circle, and in their rumbe, may be conſiderable; yet in moſt Voyages it is not: as in the forenamed Example of two places in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of 40 degrees, the difference by calculation is found to be but one degree 54/100, which is ſcarce conſiderable in the whole Voyage, being 52 degrees. Thirdly, it wil be ſomewhat difficult, &amp; it requires great curioſity in drawing of thoſe lines preſcribed by them ſo exactly, that you may come to the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the diſtance any thing neer. Laſtly, all that trouble is needleſſe. For though in calculation this diſtance muſt be found out firſt, that ſo you may find out the reſt of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions following: yet in this way I am about to ſhew that which follows, no way depends upon the true knowledge of this diſtance: it ſhal be ſufficient therefore for the preſent, to tel you, that this way is always ſomewhat the neereſt way.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond of theſe Propoſitions, which is to know the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117362:30"/> angle of poſition from the one place to the other.<note place="margin">The angle of poſition is needleſs in this operation.</note> Though this muſt be found out in calculation before you can proceed any further, yet in this work it is more needleſſe then the former propoſition, and therefore may be very well omitted.</p>
               <p>But now for the third Propoſition,<note place="margin">To finde out the longitudes and latitudes by which the great circle doth paſs.</note> which is the finding out by what Longitudes and Latitudes the great circle muſt paſſe between the two places, this being the very end aimed at in all the work, may be thus attained.</p>
               <p>Firſt, draw the following Quadrant A D B, and divide it into degrees; then conſider of what length your Tangent line muſt be, and accordingly ſet off your Radius from A to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward D the larger<note n="*" place="margin">You may make your tangent larger either by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your Quadrant lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius further from the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Thus in the Quadrant the line D K is a larger tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent line, which though it reach but to 45 degrees, yet by lengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the line, you may ſet on the reſt.</note> the better, but in this Quadrant, the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius is A R) and this Radius is always a tangent of 45 degrees. Then from the point R, draw the line R T parallel to the ſide of the Quadrant A B: this line R T is the Tangent line which you muſt divide into degrees, as you ſee in the figure by drawing ſtraight lines from the Center A to the limbe of the Quadrant. Then transferre this line to the ſides of the Quadrant A B and A D, and then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in the center A, open the other to the ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in the line A B or A D and draw the arches. Now you muſt know that theſe arches are the parallels of latitude; and the ſtraight lines drawn from the Center, are Meridian lines, or the lines of longitude. The arches of latitude you muſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as in the figure: but the lines of longitude you may num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as your occaſion requires.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:117362:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <hi>This is a projection of a part of the Globe in</hi> plano <hi>by Naturall Tangents: You may if you pleaſe, when occaſion requires, divide a Circle into foure Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drants, and draw the lines of Longitude from the Center, and number them to</hi> 360, <hi>and likewiſe deſcribe the Circles of Latitude round about the Center, and you may make this Projection as large or as little as you will by the Table of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Tangents, if you lengthen or ſhorten your Radius.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:117362:31"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A Table of <hi>Naturall Tangents</hi> The Radius being 1000 parts.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>D.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">D.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">D.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Tang.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">D.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Tange<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>017</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>445</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>1,036</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>02,605</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>035</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>466</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>1,072</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>02,747</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>052</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>488</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>1,112</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>02, 904</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>070</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>510</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>1, 150</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>03, 078</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>087</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>532</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>1, 192</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>03, 271</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>554</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>1,235</cell>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>03,487</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>123</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>577</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>1, 280</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>03,732</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>141</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>601</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>1, 327</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>04, 011</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>158</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>624</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>1,376</cell>
                        <cell>77</cell>
                        <cell>04,331</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>176</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>649</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>1,428</cell>
                        <cell>78</cell>
                        <cell>04,705</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>194</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>675</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>1,483</cell>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                        <cell>05,144</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>213</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>700</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>1, 540</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>05, 671</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>231</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>727</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>1,600</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>06, 313</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>249</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>754</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>1,664</cell>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>07,115</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>268</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>781</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>1, 732</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                        <cell>08, 144</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>287</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>810</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>1,804</cell>
                        <cell>84</cell>
                        <cell>09, 514</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>306</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>839</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>1, 881</cell>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>11,430</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>325</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>869</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>1,963</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                        <cell>14,300</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>344</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>900</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>2, 050</cell>
                        <cell>87</cell>
                        <cell>19,081</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>364</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>933</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>2, 144</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>28, 636</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>384</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>966</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>2, 246</cell>
                        <cell>89</cell>
                        <cell>57,290</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>404</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>1000</cell>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                        <cell>2,356</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Infinite</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>424</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Rad.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>2, 475</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let your Radius be of what length you pleaſe, firſt divide it into</hi> 10 <hi>equall parts, and then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divide each of thoſe parts into</hi> 10, <hi>ſo you ſhall have</hi> 100 <hi>parts in your line, then you may, if you can, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide each of theſe</hi> 100 <hi>parts into</hi> 10, <hi>ſo you ſhall have</hi> 1000, <hi>But this laſt diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be needleſſe, for you may by your eye gueſſe at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion ill part. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus fitted your Scale of equal parts, you may prick down the line of Tangents out of this Table. Note after you are paſt</hi> 45 <hi>degrees in the Table, the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, ſhews the whole Radius, or how many times the whole Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius is contained therein, and the three following Figures, the parts to be reckond upon the Scale as before. You will finde this Table neceſſary, either when you would make a large Tangent line to ſerve for places onely neer the Pole; Or when you would make a very little Tangent line that ſo you may bring in the degrees neer the Equinoctiall into your Quadrant.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:117362:32"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The flank be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made will ſerve for many examples, ſo that the work wil be very eaſie.</note>Having thus drawn this blank Quadrant, you muſt ſet down therin the two places you are to ſail between, according to their latitudes and longitudes, and then onely by your ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler draw a ſtraight line from the one place to the other, and this ſtraight line will repreſent the great circle which paſſeth between the two places, and will exactly croſſe thoſe degrees of longitude and latitude, which you muſt ſail by.</p>
               <p>For the example<note place="margin">Example.</note> and proof hereof, I ſhal take Mr. <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods</hi> example of a voyage from the <hi>Summer Ilands</hi> to the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> the latitude of the <hi>Summer-Ilands</hi> is 32 degrees 25 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, let the longitude thereof be ſuppoſed to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>00 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, the latitude of the <hi>Lizard</hi> is neer 50 degrees, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of longitude betvveen the tvvo places is ſuppoſed to be 70 degrees, ſo that the longitude of the <hi>Lizard</hi> vvil be 10 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. And it is required to know by what longitudes and latitudes the arch of a great circle drawn between theſe two places doth paſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The working of the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>Firſt, let the line A B repreſent the meridian of the <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ilands,</hi> upon which you muſt marke out their latitude 32 degrees, 25 minutes at B, and becauſe the longitude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is 300: ſet down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>00 at the end of the line A B, ſo the <hi>Summer-Ilands</hi> ſhal be ſet down according to their longitude and latitude: then count ſtill forward the degrees of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of longitude till you come to 70 degrees in the limbe of the quadrant, and there draw the line A C 70, this line will repreſent the meridian of the <hi>Lizard,</hi> and upon this line you muſt marke out the latitude of the <hi>Lizard,</hi> which is 50 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees at C, then lay your ruler to theſe two markes at B and C, and draw the ſtraight line B C. This line B C will repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the arch of the great circle between theſe two places, and if you guide your eye along in this line, you may readily and truly perceive by what longitudes and latitudes you ſhould ſail, for marke well where this line croſſeth the arches of latitude, and the lines of longitude, and that ſhews the true longitudes and latitudes of the arch of the great circle, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your deſire.<note place="margin">The proof.</note> Now the truth hereof will more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear, if you compare the latitudes and longitudes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117362:32"/> which this line interſecteth with this table thereof calculated by Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">In the tenth Probleme of ſailing by the arch of a great circle.</note> 
                  <hi>Norwood</hi> for every fifth degree of longitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="3">
                           <hi>Longitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>Latitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">De.</cell>
                        <cell rows="16">
                           <hi>or difference of longitude.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">D.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>305</cell>
                        <cell>05</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>315</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>320</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>325</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>330</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>335</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>07</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>340</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>04</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>345</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>350</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>355</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>360</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>005</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>010</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Now you may hereby ſee, that the line B C in the point G doth croſſe the 305, or the 5 degree of longitude from B al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at the arch of 36 degrees of latitude, juſt as the table ſhewes it ſhould, at 35 degrees, 52 minutes of latitude. Again, the line B C doth croſſe the 310 or the 10 degree of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude from B in the point <hi>h,</hi> almoſt at the arch of 39 degrees of latitude agreeing with the table which ſhews it to be in 38 degrees 51 minutes. And ſo in all the reſt it ſo neerly agrees, that if you take any care in making of this blank Map to draw the arches of latitude, and the degrees of longitude truly, you ſhal not need to uſe any calculation, though you are wel skil'd therin, for the thing hereby may be much more exactly known, then the courſe of a ſhip can be ſteered.</p>
               <p>For the further explaining of this, take another example,<note place="margin">An example of two places in one parallel.</note> which ſhal be of a parallel courſe. Suppoſe two places to be ſcituate in the parallel of 40 degrees of North latitude, and their difference of longitude to be 70 degrees, the one being in 300, the other in 10 degrees of longitude, and it is deſired to know what longitudes and latitudes the arch of a great circle being drawn between theſe two places will paſſe through.</p>
               <p>To perform this, firſt in the line A B marke out the latitude of the one place which is 40 degrees at E. Then in that ſame
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117362:33"/> arch count 70 degrees of longitude, from E to F, and there make a mark for the other place, thus the two places being ſet down upon the blanke map according to their latitudes and longitudes, draw a ſtraight line from E to F, and this will repreſent the great circle, which is to be drawn between the two places, and the interſections which it maketh with the arches of latitude, and the lines of longitude will ſhew the true longitudes and latitudes by which this great circle ought to paſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Proofe of the worke, by its agreement with calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>Now for the proof hereof though Mr. <hi>Norwood</hi> in his Book, hath not calculated the longitudes and latitudes of the arch of a great circle in ſuch an example as this: yet his rules ſhew how to do it, and according to them I have calculated this table, ſo that you might ſee the exactneſſe of this way by its agreement with the table.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="3">
                           <hi>Longitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="4">
                           <hi>Latitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">De.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">De.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">100 parts</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell rows="16">
                           <hi>or difference of longit.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell rows="16">
                           <hi>theſe minutes are in</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>305</cell>
                        <cell>05</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>315</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>320</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>325</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>330</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>335</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>335</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>340</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>345</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>350</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>355</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>360</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>005</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>010</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Note if you draw lines by every degree of longitude in the blanck Map, as there is by every degree of latitude, you may then finde out the latitude of the great circle for every degree of longitude. But this paines wil be needleſſe, yet the lines may be for ſome uſe, for if your two places differ more in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude then they do in longitude, then it will be your better way to ſet down by what longitudes the great circle doth paſs at every fourth or fift degree of latitude.</p>
               <p>Now that the longitudes and latitudes of a great circle thus
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117362:33"/> found out will be exact enough for the Seamans uſe,<note place="margin">The longitudes &amp; latitudes of the arch thus found out wil be exact e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</note> if you be any thing carefull and handſome in drawing of the lines of latitude and longitude true, obſerve what Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">See Maſter <hi>Norwood</hi> in his Problemes of ſaling by a great circle. <hi>Prob.</hi> 9. latter end.</note> 
                  <hi>Norwood</hi> ſaith to this purpoſe, his words are theſe.</p>
               <p>Having ſpoken before the calculation hereof: but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that hath hitherto been ſaid, it may ſeem hard to direct a ſhip, and to keep ſuch a rekoning as may be agreeable to this method of ſailing. And indeed as it is in a manner im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, ſo neither is it neceſſary that a ſhip ſhould alwayes perſevere exactly in the arch of a great circle. It may ſuffice, and it is almoſt the ſame in effect, if a ſhip be ſo directed that ſhee go neer this arch. Which how to do he ſheweth in the next probleme, wherein I ſhall follow him, onely whereas he directs you to finde out the longitudes and latitudes of the arch of the great circle, by calculation, I have ſhewed you how to ſave that labour, and yet finde it out ſufficiently exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your uſe.</p>
               <p>Having therefore found but the longitudes and latitudes by which the great circle muſt paſſe, as is before ſhewed,<note place="margin">How to uſe the longitude and latitude being found out.</note> you muſt likewiſe provide you a blank Sea-chart, drawing it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the leſſer or larger Meridian line, as is before ſhewed. Then prick down in this chart the latitudes through which the arch of the great circle doth paſſe at every tenth degree of longitude Then if your chart be of the leſſer ſize, you may with your compaſſes draw an arch of a circle through thoſe pricks, and this arch will repreſent the great circle between the two places. But if your chart be of the larger ſize, and ſo your compaſſes be not large enough, to draw this circle; or elſe you are forced in regard of the length of the voyage to make two or three charts for it, then you may prick down the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudes and latitudes of the great circle for every fift degree of longitude, and with your ruler, draw little ſtraight lines from one prick to another, and yet theſe lines wil repreſent the great circle wel enough. And thus the great circle being drawn upon the chart, you may eaſily by the former directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the uſe of the chart, ſee what point you muſt ſteer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117362:34"/> at the beginning of your voyage, and afterward altering your courſe by halfe a point at a time,<note place="margin">It is not good to ſteere upon quarter points, becauſe they are not ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in the Compaſs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it good to alter your courſe too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</note> you may keep as neer to the arch of the great circle, as either you need or can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to do.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe Mr. <hi>Norwood</hi> hath ſufficiently explained this in the example of the <hi>Summer-Ilands,</hi> and the <hi>Lizard,</hi> I ſhall paſſe by that example, onely ſetting it down upon the chart, and referre you to his directions, and ſhew you the like in a parallel courſe.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe you were to ſail from the coaſt of <hi>Virginia</hi> to the coaſt of <hi>Portugal</hi> between two places lying in the parallel of 40 degrees north latitude, and the difference of longitude between them is 70 degrees, the firſt place being in<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe places are not ſet down accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their true Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Long. which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</note> 300 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of longitude, and the ſecond place in 10 degrees of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, and you would ſail by the arch of a great circle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two places.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:117362:35"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The ſeverall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where you alter your courſe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The courſe you ſteere.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>The diſt. or way ſailed.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>The Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="3">
                           <hi>The Latitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">P.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 from <hi>N</hi> to <hi>a</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>305</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 from <hi>a</hi> to <hi>c</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>315</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 from <hi>c</hi> to <hi>e</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E b N</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>325</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 from <hi>e</hi> to <hi>f</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                        <cell>332</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5 from <hi>f</hi> to <hi>g</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Eaſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>335</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6 from <hi>g</hi> to <hi>h</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Eaſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>338</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7 from <hi>h</hi> to <hi>i</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                        <cell>345</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8 from <hi>i</hi> to <hi>k,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E by S</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>355</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9 from <hi>k</hi> to <hi>l</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>005</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10 from <hi>l</hi> to <hi>P</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E S E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>09</cell>
                        <cell>010</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Summe</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell cols="3"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt not thinke to finde theſe courſes and diſtances which I have ſet down in this table,<note place="margin">How to work upon a larger. Chart.</note> can be ſo exactly found out by the former generall chart, which is drawn by che leſſer Meridian line, but if you draw two or three blank charts by the larger meridian line, in two or three ſheets of paper, you may then finde them out eaſily, and as exactly as need be. In theſe ſeveral charts, you may ſet down your dayly courſes and diſtances, and then when you pleaſe you may prick down the ſumme of theſe reckonings upon the generall chart, and thereby the better ſee whereabouts you are in reſpect of your whole voyage. Thus you may eaſily, know the ſeverall parts, and the total ſumme of your voyage at any time.</p>
               <p>Or elſe you may keep account of ſuch a voyage as this, and finde out all your diſtances and courſes upon one blank chart,<note place="margin">A way to avoid drawing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Charts.</note> drawn in a ſheet of paper, (or leſs if you pleaſe) as in the figure following. But I would not wiſh you to ſcant your ſelf to ſo ſmall a chart as this is, this being ſo little, onely in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117362:36"/> regard of the littleneſſe of the book, and ſo the lines are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, oftner then otherwiſe you need to do.</p>
               <p>Now in this following chart, being fitted to the latitudes you muſt ſail under, firſt ſet down your firſt place N accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the latitude thereof, which is 40 degrees, then prick down the latitude of the great circle, at the firſt fift degree of longitude, which is 41 degrees, 34 minutes at <hi>a,</hi> then laying your ruler from N to <hi>a,</hi> pricke out the line N <hi>a,</hi> which will repreſent the arch of the circle from N to <hi>a.</hi> Then the latitude of the circle for the next 5 degrees, is 42 degrees. 53 minutes, or 88/100 parts, this muſt be ſet down at R, and then draw the pricked line from <hi>a</hi> to R, ſo you have the arch of the circle from N to R. Now if you would know what courſe you muſt ſteer: by your ſcale of rumbes you ſhal finde that from <hi>N</hi> to <hi>a,</hi> the courſe is <hi>E N E,</hi> and the diſtance from N to <hi>a</hi> meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the meridian line, is 4 degrees, 1/10, or 41 tenths of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. And here now becauſe the rumb line doth run above the arch of the circle at <hi>a,</hi> I leave this courſe and alter my courſe halfe a point more towards the eaſt.</p>
               <p>Alſo in regard of the ſhortneſſe of the chart, I am forced to break off the arch of the great circle at <hi>a,</hi> and ſet down the latitude thereof in the firſt meridian again at <hi>a,</hi> and ſet down the latitude thereof in the firſt meridian again at <hi>a,</hi> drawing a line from <hi>a</hi> to <hi>a,</hi> then 5 degrees from this meridian that is 10 degrees,<note place="margin">Take theſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes out of the Table. <hi>page</hi> 56.</note> from the firſt place N, I ſet down the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the great circle, which is 42 degrees, 53 minutes or 88 parts at <hi>b,</hi> and 5 degr. from <hi>b,</hi> that is 15 degrees from N, I ſet down the latitude of the circle, which is 43 degrees, 55 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, or 92 at <hi>c,</hi> and prick out the lines <hi>a b</hi> and <hi>b c,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the great circle, then by a ſcale of rumbes, I ſet off 6 rumbes and a half, which is the black line <hi>a c,</hi> which almoſt meets with the pricked circle at <hi>c,</hi> and the diſtance from <hi>a</hi> to <hi>c,</hi> is 7 degrees 7/10, as you may finde by meaſuring it in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian line. And note though the rumbe line and the arch of the circle, do not here cloſe exactly, yet it is no matter: for I have drawn it thus to even 5 and 10 degrees that it might agree with what hath been before ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:117362:36"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:117362:37"/>
               <p>Here again becauſe of the ſhortnes of the chart I am forced to break off the circle, &amp; the rumbe-line, &amp; ſet them in the firſt meridian at <hi>c,</hi> then 5 deg. from the meridian at <hi>c</hi> that is 20 deg. from N, I prick down the latitude of the arch, which is 44 deg. 42 minutes, or 70 parts, at 20; and five degrees from this 20, I prick down the latitude of the arch in that longitude, which is 45 degrees, 15 minutes, or 25 parts, at <hi>c,</hi> then I draw the pricked lines from <hi>c</hi> to 20, and from 20 to <hi>e,</hi> which repreſent the arch, and I likewiſe draw the rumble line <hi>N by E</hi> from <hi>c</hi> to <hi>e,</hi> which doth very neerly concurre with the arch at <hi>e,</hi> and the diſtance from <hi>c</hi> to <hi>e</hi> is 7 degrees, and almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/10 or as in the the table, 7 degrees, 26/100.</p>
               <p>Here again by reaſon of the ſhortneſſe of the chart, I am forced to break off again, and ſetting the latitude of this point <hi>e,</hi> in the firſt meridian at <hi>e,</hi> 5 degrees from this I ſet down the latitude of the arch of the great circle belonging to that lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, which is 45 degrees, 35 minutes, or 58 parts at 30, this meridian is 30 degrees diſtant from the firſt place at N. And then 5 degrees from this, which is 35 degrees from the firſt meridian at N, I ſet down the latitude of the arch, which is 45 degrees, 41 minutes, or 68 parts at <hi>g,</hi> then I draw the pricked lines from <hi>e</hi> to 30, and from 30 to <hi>g;</hi> this repreſents the arch, now at the point <hi>e,</hi> I alter my courſe half a point more to the Eaſtward, therefore by the ſcale of rumbes, ſetting off 7 points and a half from the point <hi>e,</hi> I draw the line <hi>e f,</hi> which is <hi>N by E,</hi> half a point to the Eaſt: and having ſayled upon this point from <hi>e</hi> to <hi>f,</hi> the latitude wil be 45 degrees, 42 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, or 70 parts, and the difference of longitude from <hi>e</hi> is 7 degrees, and the diſtance from E is 4 degrees, 9/10, but the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of longitude from the firſt place at N, is 32 degrees.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, becauſe now I am as farre to the Northward as the arch of the great circle will allow me, I here at <hi>f</hi> alter my courſe halfe a point more, and ſo ſail from <hi>f</hi> to <hi>g</hi> full Eaſt, ſo I have altered my longitude in all 35 degrees, and am come juſt one halfe of the voyage.</p>
               <p>Now to perform the other half, you muſt continue to do as you did before, firſt prick out the great circle, and then finde
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117362:37"/> out the rumbes you muſt ſail upon from one point to another, which you may alter now and then half a point, and ſo you may lay the Pole in the ſame order and proportion that before you raiſed it, as you may ſee by the table before, <hi>page</hi> 61.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Shewing ſome obſervations which may be of uſe in all theſe three kinds of ſayling.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſhewed you how to ſail, either by the Rumbe that leads from one place to another, or elſe by an arch of a great circle extended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two places, I ſhal now lay down ſome obſervations, which may be uſefull in either of theſe wayes of ſayling, for ſometimes it is beſt to uſe the one way, ſometimes the other, in ſome voyages it is beſt to ſail by the Rumbe, in ſome voyages it is beſt to ſail by the arch, in ſome voyages it is the beſt way to uſe both, and to keep neither to the rumbe nor to the arch exactly.</p>
               <p>In voyages to the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> though the neereſt way, be by the arch of a great circle; and though the way by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Rumbe, lies very wel: yet it is uſual in theſe voyages to ſteer wide from both theſe neerer ways, <hi>viz</hi> firſt, to ſteer much more to the Southward then the courſe lies, until they come into the latitude of the place, and then to run their courſe Weſt, until they arrive at their deſired port. And this way is very good, eſpecially when you ſail unto a little lone Iſland.<note place="margin">To get the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the winde.</note> For firſt, by ſayling toward the Line, you ſhal gain the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the <hi>Tradewind</hi> (as they call it) which doth moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly blow between the North and Eaſt, between and neer the <hi>Tropicks.</hi> Secondly, hereby you may be ſure not to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoot the Iſland you would ſayl to,<note place="margin">To avoyd over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhooting the place you go to</note> which otherwayes may eaſily be done. For it is an hard matter in a long voyage, to ſteer your courſes ſo exactly, and keep your account of your way ſo perfectly, as not to miſſe ſome few leagues: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:117362:38"/> if this could be done, yet the courſes and diſtances can not be ſo exactly known, becauſe the true longitudes of places one in reſpect of another is not ſo exactly found out, as is to be wiſhed for. And if by either of theſe cauſes, when you ſhall come to the end of your reckoning, you ſhal chance not to be in ſight of the Iſland, you wil then be at ſuch a loſſe, that you wil not know which way to ſail to finde it, whether Eaſtward, or Weſtward, and ſo muſt be forced to vvander at randome untill you have a ſight of ſome knovvn place, by which you may knovv hovv the Iſland bears from you. Therefore in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſuch a place as this; it is the beſt vvay to be ſure to get into the latitude of the place, a good while before you come to it, and then ſayling neer that latitude, you ſhall be ſure not to paſſe by it without a ſight of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 To get a wind.</note>In voyages from the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> the uſual way is firſt to ſail much more northerly, then the true Rumbe doth lie, and this likewiſe is to get the benefit of the wind, for as the winde lies moſt Eaſterly toward the Equinoctial, ſo it blows moſt weſterly towards the Pole: alſo this way is the neereſt way, becauſe it lies neer the arch of a great circle. But many Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men not knowing ſo much, and eſpecially keeping their rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning upon the plain chart, this convenience might prove an inconvenience to them for they are many times at their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys end 150 or 200 leagues before they are aware, and ſo might eaſily overſhoot their port, and loſe themſelves, but that they ſail to the maine land, or great Iſlands that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſſe by.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 The inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.</note>Now as for theſe cauſes you ſometimes ſtray from the rumb or arch which lies between the two places, ſo there is another conſideration which may be a ſufficient reaſon for a little wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, ſometimes out of the way, and that is the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that there is, in ſayling far upon a courſe of Eaſt or Weſt. Becauſe you muſt always depend upon your dead reckoning which is ſubject to much miſtake, having no way to correct it by obſervation. This parallel ſayling makes the journey many times ſeem tedious. As a man that travails in an unknown way, thinks the miles and the way to be longer then indeed they are,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:117362:38"/> whereas he that knows the road and how farre it is from place to place, goes on more chearfully. Therefore the labour wil not be loſt if you go ſometimes a little out of your way for this conſideration, that ſo you may have the more certainty of your account.</p>
               <p>Indeed the way of ſailing by the arch of a great circle doth very much help in this,<note place="margin">How to avoid ſailing in a parallel, partly.</note> as I have ſhewed at large in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter, but yet if you keep your ſelf in your yoyage too ſtrictly to the arch, you muſt runne much of your way in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, or very neer it. As in the example of the parallel voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in the laſt chapter, the difference of longitude between the two places being 70 degrees, if you keep to the arch, you muſt firſt ſail <hi>E N E,</hi> til you alter your longitude 5 degrees, then halfe a point more Eaſterly, til you alter your longitude 10 degrees more, then you muſt ſail <hi>N by E</hi> til you alter your longitude 10 degrees more, that is in all 25 degrees, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the 7 degrees which are ſet down half a point off the Eaſt, and the three degrees ful Eaſt, is little better then a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel courſe: then again this being the middle point of your voyage, you muſt ſail 10 degrees more in the ſame proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal courſe, ſo that of the 70 degrees of the whole voyage you muſt ſail 20 of them neer the courſe of Eaſt and Weſt.</p>
               <p>Now you ſhal ſee how eaſily this may be avoyded,<note place="margin">How to avoid ſailing in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, totally.</note> and that ſeveral wayes: firſt let the courſes be continued as before til you come to 25 degrees difference of longitude, which is at <hi>e</hi> in the laſt<note n="*" place="margin">Page 63.</note> chart, then if at this point you leave the great cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle a little, and keep on your courſe ſtil upon the 7 rumbe <hi>N by E,</hi> til you come to 35 degrees of longitude, your latitude wil be 46 degrees, 36 minutes, or 60 parts, differing from the latitude of the arch 55 minutes, but your diſtance for theſe 10 degrees of longitude wil be but 7 degrees 09/100, that is but 7/100, more then the other way, which makes but 4 miles, which makes 4 miles, which is ſo little that it is not to be regarded in reſpect of the diſtance in theſe 10 degrees, being 425 miles.</p>
               <p>Again if you begin ſooner to ſwerve from the arch, yet the difference of your way wil not be much, as you may ſee by this table which differs much from the other in the rumbes,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117362:39"/> latitudes, and longitudes, but yet it differs but little in the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſumme of the diſtances, being but 20/100, which is but 12 miles.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>Difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The courſe or Rumbe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>Diſtance or way ſayled.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>The true Longitude.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>The Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">P.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Min.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Min.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>08</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                        <cell>07</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>320</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E by N</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>335</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E by S</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>350</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>½</cell>
                        <cell>07</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>360</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E S E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>08</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>010</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="3">The Summe</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">See the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Chart, page 58.</note>Once * again if you try another way, as if you ſhould ſail from the firſt place N, in the latitude of 40 degrees, upon the 6 rumbe <hi>E N E,</hi> til you have altered your longitude 35 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which is the half of your voyage, you wil then finde your ſelfe to be at Q, in the latitude of 50 degrees, 12 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, and your diſtance or way ſayled, will be 26 degrees 63/100. Then if from this point you alter your courſe, and ſail upon the 6 rumbe Southward, again, <hi>E S E</hi> to <hi>P,</hi> your diſtance wil be as before 26 degrees 63/100, and ſo you wil come to the latitude of 40 again, being the place you deſire, ſo that your whole voyage by this reckoning wil be but 53 degrees 26/100, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> though it be ſomewhat more then the diſtance by the arch, which is 52 degrees, 08/100, yet it is leſſe then the diſtance of theſe two places, in the parallel which is 53 degrees, 62/100, and the loſſe of the way wil be wel recompenſed, eſpecially in ſailing from the <hi>Indies,</hi> by the advantage of the wind, and by the certainty you may keep off your account, ſayling alwayes upon the ſixt rumbe.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:117362:39"/>
               <p>By this alſo it appears, that the longitudes and latitudes of the arch of a great circle, and the courſes and diſtances which you are to ſail upon, in tracing thereof, may be ſufficiently found out in the tracing thereof, may be ſufficiently found out by the wayes before ſhewed, ſo that there needs no other cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation for them, ſince a ſmal wandring from them, will not alter the length of the way in any conſiderable quantity.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo you may eaſily avoid ſayling upon a courſe of Eaſt &amp; Weſt. Which way ſoever your voiage lies,<note place="margin">To avoyd ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eaſt or Weſt at any time.</note> it wil be your beſt way to ſteer no neerer to the Eaſt or Weſt, then the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> rumbe from the meridian. For ſo you may by your obſervation of the latitude, correct your account which otherwiſe you cannot do, and in doing thus, you vvil not go much out of your vvay. For ſuppoſe you vvere to ſail betvveen tvvo places, under the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial line, ſo that the direct and neereſt way between theſe two places, lies ful Eaſt and Weſt, yet you may ſayl be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two places upon the ſeventh Rumbe, and go not much out of your way. For example, let the two places be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant 10 degrees, if you firſt ſail the one half of your way up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 7 Rumbe, that is till you have altered your longitude 5 degrees, you wil raiſe the Pole very neer one degree, <hi>viz.</hi> 994/1000, and your diſtance or way ſayled will be but 5 degrees, 1/10 almoſt, <hi>viz.</hi> 5 degrees, 098/1000. Then if you alter your courſe, and ſo lay the pole as much upon the 7 Rumbe the other way; ſo you wil come to the place deſired, having run the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as before: thus in a voyage of 10 degrees, or 100 tenths or double leagues, you go not fully 2 tenths out of your way, which is not one in 50, which wil be wel recompenſed, becauſe in ſailing thus upon the 7 Rumbe, you may by the obſervation of the latitude correct your account. For this rumbe raiſeth or depreſſe the Pole almoſt one degree in ſayling of five, which wil ſerve very wel to correct your account by, and therefore I wil not perſwade you to go any further, out of your way. And if you direct your courſe according to this rule, this is the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt that you need go out of the way. For in all other places, the arch of the great circle, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the neereſt way between two places, doth always lie ſomewhat between the Pole, and the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:117362:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> parallel of Eaſt and Weſt, and therefore in raiſing the Pole upon the 7 Rumbe, you wil not go altogether ſo much out of your way, if you obſerve to incline your courſe alwayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Pole. Thus you ſee you need not ſayl directly Eaſt or Weſt at any time unleſſe it be when you feare you ſhal paſs by ſome little lone Iſland, as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4 Make uſe of the Sea chart and the Map, or Globe <hi>in plano, pag.</hi> 52. both together.</note>In voyages neer the Pole it is beſt to guide your ſelf as neer the arch of the great circle as you can, having reſpect to the former conſiderations. And in theſe voyages your beſt way wil be to keep your reckonings, both upon the Chart and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oe the Map, ſo the one wil help the defects of the other. As for example, the Rumbes from one place to another, are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to be found out upon the chart, but the diſtances of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the arch between them wil be found out more eaſily by the Map. For the places being ſet upon it according to their longitudes and latitudes, wil be more compoſed and hold bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conformity to the Globe, being in a manner the ſame with it, eſpecially within 10 or 20 degrees from the Pole. Thus then if you are to ſail upon diſcovery, and not to a certain place, your beſt way wil be; by the rumbe which you ſail upon, and by the latitude which you finde by obſervation, to finde out the longitude of the place you are in at any time by the chart, and then ſetting down this place, according to its lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude and latitude thus found out, upon the Map, you may more readily ſee its diſtance and poſition from any other place. But if you are to ſail to a certain place, whoſe longitude and latitude is known, then it wil be beſt, to ſet the place down firſt in the Map, and ſo to finde out the longitudes and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the great circle between them, which being pricked down upon the chart, you may ſee how to ſteer your courſes to the place appointed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5 To find out if there be any current.</note>In all your voyages it wil be a good way to keep your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts upon two blanck charts, upon the one, you may keep your dead reckoning, upon the other, your corrected account. And the benefit hereof wil be this: if you be careful to keep your dead reckoning outward, and homewards true, you may thereby whether there be any current between the two places,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:117362:40"/> and which way that current ſets, and how faſt it runnes. For if there be a current between the places you ſail to, which way ſoever the current ſets, your reckonings outward and home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward wil not agree, and indeed you can keepe no good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your way, til you know which way and how faſt the current runnes.</p>
               <p>For example: firſt, ſuppoſe the current runnes Eaſt 12 miles a day, and you ſayl againſt this current according to your account, by your Log-line (which is the beſt meaſure of your dead reckoning) 60 miles Weſt in a day, your true pace or diſtance wil be but 48 miles in a day, becauſe the current wil ſet you back 12 miles, which ſubſtracted from 60, there remains but 48. On the contrary, if you ſayl Eaſtward in this current, (and ſo ſayl with it) 60 miles a day according to your log-line, then your true motion wil be 72 miles a day, becauſe the current wil ſet you forward 12 miles more then you ſeem to goe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe the current run Eaſt one mile an hour, if you ſayl in this current <hi>N E</hi> or <hi>S E,</hi> look how many hours you ſail, ſo many miles the ſtream wil ſet you more forward in your longitude, then you are avvare of; and yet your lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, vvil fal out according to your account. On the other ſide if you ſayl <hi>N W</hi> or <hi>S W</hi> in this current, the current vvil drive you backvvard ſo many miles, and yet your latitude vvil be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your account.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if the current run upon any rumbe betvveen the meridian, and the Eaſt or Weſt, then your true motion vvil differ from your dead reckoning, and alſo from your account by obſervation, both in longitude and latitude, ſo that until you knovv in ſome ſort both vvhich vvay and hovv faſt the current runs, you can never keep a good account of your vvay and the onely way to finde out the current is to keep a good account by the log-line outvvard and homevvard, and by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this dovvn upon your blanck chart you may plainly ſee vvhich vvay the current runs, and hovv faſt, as <hi>Maſter Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> hath very vvel demonſtrated in the end of his <hi>Sea-mans Practice.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:117362:41"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6 To alter your courſe as ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame as you can.</note>In moſt voyages, it wil be good to keep your courſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, (or as much as you can) upon one and the ſame rumb, for ſo your account wil be more eaſily and certainly kept. For at every ſhifting of your courſe, the true point that you are in, cannot be ſo certainly known, but that you may miſreckon ſomewhat both in the latitude and longitude thereof. For the latitude by which you have the moſt certainty of your place, may be miſtaken 5 or 10 minutes, by any inſtruments ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily uſed, and this may cauſe 20 or 30 minutes errour in the longitude, and this errour, at every changing of your courſe, may as wel chance to be increaſed, as to be ballanced one time with another, whereas if you ſteer your courſe conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon one rumbe, as it wil avoyd the trouble of drawing ſo many rumbe lines, ſo there can be no greater errour in your account, then there ſhal happen to be in the laſt obſervation of the latitude, which cannot be much. But if you are forced to ſhift your courſe in regard of the wind, then in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of your account, obſerve the rule in the ſecond caſe of the ſixt Propoſition of the plain chart, drawing a ſtraight line from your firſt place to the place you are then in.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7 To gain ſight of land when you can.</note>It vvil not be amiſſe as often as you can, to get a ſight of ſuch Capes, Headlands or Iſlands, as lye neer your courſe, which being ſtanding marks, wil give you certain knowledg, vvhereabouts you are, and ſo you may the better direct your courſe and perfect your account.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">8 To obſerve the variation of your Compaſs.</note>Laſtly, you muſt have an eſpecial care of your compaſſe, that it be every way perfectly and exactly made, and likewiſe you muſt be as careful, that you ſteer your courſe exactly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that rumbe you reckon on; to vvhich end, not onely the Steerſ-man muſt be diligent to keep the ſhip to the courſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, but you muſt be frequent in obſerving the variation of the compaſſe, vvhich may be ſo vvel performed by the Sea rings in uſe among Sea-men, that no Inſtrument can be devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fitter for the purpoſe, this variation being knovvn, muſt be allovved for in your account, that ſo you may knovv the true rumbe you ſail upon, vvithout vvhich there can be no true account kept.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:117362:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP VII.</hi> Of ſayling by a great Circle.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the way already propoſed for the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the arch of a great circle,<note place="margin">Another way to find out the longitudes and latitudes of the arch of a great circle.</note> between two places, is the moſt eaſie and plaineſt way that can be, yet becauſe it is not ſo general as to take in all places, but is onely to be uſed when the two places are both, on the one ſide of the Equinoctiall: as alſo it may ſeem ſomewhat defective, becauſe it doth not ſhew the diſtances of places; I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here added this ſecond way, partly for variety, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſupply the defects of the former. But as this way is more artificial, ſo it is more difficult, both in the demonſtration, and practiſe, which cannot be avoided. But you may the better bear with it, becauſe you wil ſeldome be forced to uſe this way, but may very wel content your ſelf with the other in moſt voyages.</p>
               <p>This and all other queſtions of this nature, concerning the reſolution of any ſpherical triangle, may very eaſily be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Globe: but becauſe the Globe is a chargeable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, and ſo every one cannot have it: therefore ſeverall men have for ſeverall uſes invented ſeverall wayes to project the Globe upon a Plane. You may ſee the ſeverall projections thereof in Mr. <hi>Gunters</hi> book of the Sector. The fitteſt for this purpoſe wil be that of <hi>Gemma Friſius,</hi> which is moſt uſed in Maps of the whole world, the projection whereof is, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, draw the circle A D B C,<note place="margin">How to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Globe <hi>in plano.</hi>
                  </note> and divide it into four parts or quadrants, by the croſſe diameters, A B and C D, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide each quadrant, into 90 degrees and number them as in the figure, then if you keep one end of your ruler fixed at the point A, and lay the other end to the ſeveral degrees in the lower Semicircle, D B C, ſo you ſhal divide the Diameter C D into its parts, which are half tangents. In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:117362:42"/> if you keep one end of your ruler fixed in the point C, and lay the other end to the ſeverall degrees of the Semicircle A D B, you may divide the diameter A B into halfe tangents.</p>
               <p>Having thus divided the circumference and the diameters, they muſt guide you in the drawing of the meridians and the parallels,<note place="margin">How to draw the Meridians and Parallels.</note> which are all parts of perfect circles, and you may finde their centers by theſe three points. Firſt, for the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they all concurre in both the Poles A and B, and their third point is their correſpondent degree in the diameter C D. Then for the parallels, two of their points are their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in the outward circle, and their third point is their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent degree in the diameter A B. By theſe three points you may finde the center, and ſo draw the arch as is ſhewed in the firſt chapter. But to ſave that labour, you muſt know, that the centers all lie in the diameter lines, which muſt be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded beyond the circle, and then the centers are thus found out. The diameter C D being divided into half tangents as before, if for every degree you account two, beginning from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter E, ſo you ſhal have the centers of the meridians. Then if you ſet one foot of your compaſſes in that center, and open the other to the Pole A or B, it wil paſſe through the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent degree, or third point in the diameter C D: on the other ſide of the center, ſo the meridian wil be drawn upon the one ſide. Then with the ſame diſtance of your compaſſes, you muſt draw the other anſwerable to that on the other ſide. Then keeping your compaſſes yet at the ſame diſtance, ſet one foot in the center E, and with the other, marke the diameter A B, both above and below, and theſe markes ſhal be the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the parallels. Then ſet one foot of your compaſſes in theſe centers, and cloſe your compaſſes, til the other foot reach to that degree of latitude in the outward circle and ſo draw that arch from ſide to ſide And if you finde that the arches thus drawn, do paſſe exactly through their three reſpective points, in the circle and diameter, your work is true, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>And thus you may eaſily doe for any other degree under 45, but when you come to the degrees above 45, then you muſt extend the line C D, and laying one end of your ruler to the point A, and the other to the degrees of the upper ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circle, you may divide that part of the line without the circle as you did before that part which was within, into half tangents, and ſo doubling your degree find out the center therof. Or elſe when you draw the former meridians, you may remember to turne about the compaſſes, and marke the line C D without the circle; by theſe markes you ſhal divide the line into half tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and ſo you may finde out the centers as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to help your ſelf when your compaſſes wil not reach.</note>But becauſe ſome of theſe centers, wil fall ſo farre without the circle, that your compaſſes will not reach them; you may then bridle a thin ruler, that wil bend, with a double ſtring like a croſſe bow, and then by tvviſting the ſtring together, you may by little and little, ſet it to what bent you pleaſe, till it ſhal cut the three points of your arch you would draw, and then vvith your pen, you may dravv your arch, vvhich if the ruler be all of one thickneſſe, and ſo bend in all places alike, it vvil be very true. Your compaſſes vvil reach the centers ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvel, til you come to 60 degrees, but aftervvard you muſt be forced to uſe this or ſome ſuch like way to help your ſelf. The larger you make your draught, and the more meridians and parallels you draw in it, ſo much the better it is, therefore if you can, make it ſo large that you may draw meridians and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:117362:43"/> parallels through every degree, which you may do very wel in a ſheet of large paper in a leſſer draught, you may draw every ſecond degree, which is the leaſt I would wiſh you to do.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, to ſave time and labour in drawing of theſe blanks for every queſtion: when you have made a little triall and know how to draw them, then draw two good large ones of one and the ſame ſize, which you may do very well by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame lines in both, before you ſtir your compaſſes from their diſtances: then ſix the one of theſe to the other by their centers ſo that they may be turned round, and the uppermoſt of theſe being drawn in fine thin paper, and a little oyled, you may eaſily ſee through it all the lines of the other. And thus you ſhal have an<note n="*" place="margin">This wil be ſomewhat like Mr. <hi>Blagraves</hi> Mathematicall Jewell.</note> Inſtrument whereby this and moſt other queſtions of ſpherical triangles may be reſolved.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſhewed the drawing of this projection, I ſhal now come to ſhew you the uſe of it in ſeverall examples. The firſt example ſhall be the fore-mentioned voyage from the <hi>Summer-Iſlands,</hi> to the <hi>Lizard,</hi> the latitude of the <hi>Summer-Iſlands</hi> being 32 degrees, 25 minutes North,<note place="margin">The uſe of this projection in finding out the great circle.</note> and the latitude of the <hi>Lizard,</hi> being 50 degrees North, and their difference of longitude being 70 degrees, and it is required to know firſt the Latitudes and Longitudes by which the arch of a great circle drawn between theſe two places doth paſſe. Secondly, the angle of poſition from the firſt place to the ſecond. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the neereſt diſtance between the two places.</p>
               <p>To perform this, firſt you muſt ſet down upon your draught,<note place="margin">Firſt example.</note> the firſt place which is the <hi>Summer-Iſlands,</hi> according to the latitude thereof which is 32 degrees, 25 minutes in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt circle at S.<note n="*" place="margin">Note well which way the firſt place beares from the ſecond.</note> And herein you muſt regard how the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place doth beare from the firſt If the ſecond place lie Weſt from the firſt, then you muſt ſet down the firſt place on the Eaſt or right ſide of the circle: but if the ſecond place lie Eaſtward from the firſt, as it doth in this example, then you muſt ſet down the firſt place on the Weſt-ſide of the circle, as it is here at S. Then from the point S through the center E, draw the diameter line S E K, and croſſe it at right angles with the line M E N. Then accounting 70 degrees (which is the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:117362:44"/> difference of longitude of the two places) in the diameter C E from C to 70, mark that meridian arch, &amp; thereupon mark out the latitude of the other place which is 50 degrees at L. Thus the two places are ſet down according to their latitudes and the difference of their longitudes at S and L. Now to help you to draw the arch of a great circle between theſe two places S &amp; L, you have theſe three points S L &amp; K, by which you may finde the center of the arch which is at M, in the line N M, therefore ſet one foot of your compaſſes in M, and opening the other to any of the three points, draw the arch S L K. This arch is the great circle that paſſeth through theſe two places, by which you ſhal finde all the things deſired.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The longitudes and latitudes of the arch.</note>As firſt, if you would know by what longitudes and latitudes this arch doth paſſe (which is the thing moſt needful to be known) if you trace the way of this arch, through the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and parallels of the draught, you wil finde them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the former table hereof for every fifth or tenth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. For at 10 degrees of longitude from S, the arch paſſeth through 39 degrees of latitude: at 20, through 43 ½, and ſo of the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The angle of poſition.</note>Secondly, if you would know the angle of poſition from S to L, then obſerve in what point the arch S L K doth croſſe the line N M, which is at T, then take the diſtance N T, and meaſure it in the ſemidiameter C E from C toward E, and it wil reach almoſt to 49 degrees, which ſhews the angle of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be North-Eaſterly almoſt 49 degrees.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The diſtance of the places.</note>Thirdly, if you would know the diſtance of the two places, you muſt with your compaſſes take the diſtance of the two places S and L, and meaſuring it in that meridian, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with the angle of poſition, <hi>viz.</hi> 49 degrees, you ſhall finde it wil reach from A to V, now if you reckon the degrees of the parallels of latitude from A to this point V, you ſhal have the diſtance which is 53 degrees and a half.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe you may meaſure any part of this arch S L, in this meridian A V, if you always ſet one foot in S, and open the other to the point required, and then ſet one foot in A, and the other wil ſhew the diſtance of that place. Thus the diſtances
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:117362:44"/> wil be found out as exactly as by any other Geometrical way, but in regard of the ſmalneſſe of the projection, you may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake ſome fevv miles or leagues.</p>
               <p>But if you vvere to ſayl from the <hi>Lizard</hi> to the <hi>Summer-Iſlands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The difference in ſayling for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by the arch.</note> then you muſt firſt ſet dovvn the latitude of the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> on the other ſide of the circle (as I noted before) &amp; ſo the vvork vvil fal out much as it did before, for the longitudes and latitudes of the arch vvil be the ſame, only accounting them backvvards, the diſtance vvil be the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> 53 degrees and a half, onely it muſt be meaſured in another meridian, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the angle of poſition from the <hi>Lizard,</hi> vvhich vvil be about 81 degrees, ſo that in effect, all is the ſame, onely the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of poſition, vvhich is of little uſe, but to finde out the ſcale of the diſtances. So that if you regard it vvel, one la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vvil ſerve to finde your vvay outvvard and homevvard.</p>
               <p>I might here ſhevv you hovv to perform the parallel queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but becauſe ſuch queſtions may vvith more eaſe and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty be performed by the former vvay, I ſhal not ſpend time about it, I ſhal onely inſtance in tvvo ſorts of voyages, vvhich cannot be performed by the other projection, and in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as theſe there vvil be ſome need of this vvay, and not elſe. Firſt, vvhen one of the places is under the Equinoctial, and the other tovvard one of the poles. The other is vvhen the one place hath North latitude and the other South.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe you were to ſail from the Iſland of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Example of 2 places in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of ſcituation.</note> which lies under the Equinoctial, and hath about 35 degrees of longitude to the <hi>Straights</hi> of <hi>Magellan,</hi> which hath about 53 degrees of South latitude, and differs in longitude from the former place 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> degrees to the Weſt-ward: now it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to finde out the arch of the great circle between theſe two places, and the longitudes and latitudes of this arch, with the angle of poſition, and the diſtances of the two places.</p>
               <p>To perform this, firſt ſet down the Iſle of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> which is under the Equinoctial, at the one end of the Equinoctial line at D, then accounting 90 degrees of longitude from D to E, there is the meridian of the Straights of <hi>Magellan,</hi> whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you muſt mark out the latitude thereof, which is 53 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:117362:45"/> at W, ſo you ſhal have theſe three points D W C, by which you may finde the center, and draw the arch D W C, now this part of the circle from D to W, is the arch of the great circle, which lies between theſe two places; by which you may finde all the other things required.</p>
               <p>As firſt for the longitudes and latitudes of this arch, they are found out by noting where it croſſeth the circles of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude in the draught, which you ſhal finde for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tenth degree to be as in this table.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>Latitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Deg</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>D.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>m.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, for the angle of<note n="*" place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude being juſt 90 deg. the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of poſition is ready mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in the ſemidiameter E B being the diſtance B W, which is 37 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, but at other times muſt follow the rule.</note> poſition between the two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, this is ſhewed by the arch DW croſſing the Semidiameter E B, ſo that if you take the diſtance B W, and meaſure it in the diameter C D, it wil reach from C to 37 degrees, which is the angle required, &amp; the ſcituation ſhews it to be South weſterly.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for the diſtance of the two places, if you take the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance D W and meaſure it in the 37 meridian line (according to the angle of of poſition) it wil reach from A to the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial line,<note place="margin">Likewiſe the diſtance D W needs no other meaſuring, but muſt needs be 90 degrees.</note> which ſhews the diſtance to be 90 degrees.</p>
               <p>The laſt example ſhal be of two places, the one being on the one ſide, and the other on the other ſide of the Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. As, ſuppoſe you were to ſail from the <hi>Summer-Iſles,</hi> to the Cape of good Hope,<note place="margin">Example of places in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcituation.</note> the latitude of the <hi>Summer-Iſles,</hi> is 32 degrees 25 North, and the latitude of the Cape of good Hope is 35 degrees ſouth, and ſuppoſe the difference of longitude between theſe two places to be 90 degrees, and it is required to find out the arch of the great circle between theſe two places, according to the longitudes and latitudes thereof, the angle of poſition and the diſtance of the tvvo places.</p>
               <p>To perform this firſt you muſt ſet down the firſt place ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the latitude thereof in the outmoſt circle at S, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:117362:45"/> draw the diameter S K, to which you muſt draw the line N M ſquirewiſe at right angles, then counting the difference of longitude which is 90 degrees from C, the meridian of the Cape of good hope wil fal in the line A B, which you muſt mark out according to its latitude 35 degrees South at X, then by theſe three points S X K, finde the center which wil be in the line M N extended, and ſo draw the arch S X K.</p>
               <p>Now firſt for the longitudes and latitudes of this arch you may finde them by ſeing how this arch doth croſſe the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of longitude and latitude in the draught, which for every tenth degree of longitude is as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Long.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>Latitude</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">
                           <hi>North Latitude decreaſing.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>02</cell>
                        <cell>05</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">
                           <hi>South Latitude increaſing.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>05</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Then for the angle of poſition, you ſhal finde it thus, mark where the arch S X K, doth croſſe the line M N, which is at Z, then with your compaſſes take the diſtance Z M, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring it in the ſemidiameter C E, you ſhal finde it wil reach from C almoſt to 60, <hi>viz.</hi> 59 degrees 25 min. South eaſterly.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for the diſtance of the two places, if you take the diſtance of the two places in the arch S X, and meaſure it in this meridian, of 60, you ſhal finde it wil reach from A to Y, which is 107 degrees and a half, or more exactly 107 degrees, 34 minutes.</p>
               <p>If you make two of theſe draughts, and joyn them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I noted before, your work wil be ſomewhat more eaſie and readily performed. For then in any queſtion of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, you need but turne the Pole of the upper paper, to the latitude of the firſt place in the under paper. Then marke out the ſecond place according to its longitude and latitude, in the meridians and parallels of the under paper. Then mark what
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:117362:46"/> circle of of the upper paper, paſſeth through theſe two places, this is the arch required. Now the longitudes and latitudes thereof, you may eaſily ſee by its croſſing the meridians and parallels of the under paper. The diſtance of the two places, you ſhal know by counting the parallels in the upper paper between the two places. The angle of poſition is known by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting where the arch doth croſſe the Equinoctiall in the upper paper.</p>
               <p>By this likewiſe moſt queſtions of Aſtronomy may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as by the place of the Sun, to know the Declination of the Sun, his right aſcenſion, and oblique aſcenſion, his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude at riſing and ſetting, and by the height of the Sun to know the Azimuth and the time of the day, with many others but becauſe ſome of theſe require more exactneſſe, then any ſuch Inſtrument wil afford: and likewiſe they are ſomewhat beſide my preſent purpoſe; I ſhal not now ſpeak of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> How to keep a perfect account.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the wayes I have already ſhewed may be ſufficient for the ſetting down of any reckoning upon your Charts: yet becauſe it may be ſome trouble, if you often alter your rumbe, to draw a new rumbe line from every point: and beſides the ſcale of the Chart being ſomewhat ſmal, you wil be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſome miſtake, in finding out the ſeveral points, and this miſtake being often committed may come to ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errour, I ſhal in this chapter ſhew you, how you may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your ſcale, and by a little help of your pen finde out theſe points moſt exactly: and ſo you may ſet them down by the latitude, and their Eaſting or Weſting, without drawing of the Rumbe lines, from point to point.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the increaſing of your ſcale, which is the chief ground whereon the certainty of your reckoning wil depend.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:117362:46"/> In the figure following (which is the ſame with the plain chart before)<note place="margin">The way to keep a perfect account is to work by a very large Scale.</note> let each ſide of the ſquare be ſuppoſed to contain but one degree of longitude or latitude (whereas before we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it to contain 10 degrees) ſo ſhal each degree by this means be divided into 100 very ſenſible parts, and be 10 times greater then the ſcale of your chart, by which means you ſhal keep your account as exactly as need be required. Then it wil be neceſſary if you uſe this as an Inſtrument to draw lines through each of theſe 100 parts, croſſing one another as thoſe ten lines do; but for the better diſtinction, you may make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tenth line bigger then the reſt, and every fifth line you may prick out. Then making the corner at A the center, draw the arch of the quadrant B P 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 D, which you may divide either into 90 degrees, or elſe into the 8 Rumbes and their quarters, and it wil be good to number them both ways, from B and D. Laſtly, you muſt provide you a thin ruler or Index which muſt be divided as the ſide of the Quadrat is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 100 equal parts. You may make this Index of a piece of thin paper, and oyl it: or it wil be better, if you get a piecc of fine cleer horn, and make a ſcale of equal parts thereon, equal to the ſides of the quadrat, and ſo faſtening it to the center A, you may turn it to any Rumbe in the arch, and very plainly ſee all the lines of the Inſtruments through it.</p>
               <p>The uſe of this Inſtrument might be ſhewed in many propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, but I ſhal onely ſhew you how to uſe it in two very neceſſary propoſitions, by the one of which you may keep your dead reckoning, by the other your true reckoning by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>To perform this or any ſuch like queſtion, you muſt firſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:117362:47"/> conſider which way your courſe is in general, and lay the Quadrat ſo that the ſides A B or A D,<note place="margin">How to work the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the inſtrument.</note> the one of them may repreſent the Meridian; and the other the line of Eaſt or Weſt as in this example, the ſide A B muſt repreſent the Meridian, and the ſide A D the line of Eaſt. Then lay your horne Index to the Rumbe in the arch, and finde out the diſtance you have ſayled, upon the ſcale of your Index. Now marke very wel the point, where your diſtance upon the ſcale ends, and what lines of the Quadrat meet in this very point, and if by your eye, you trace theſe lines to the ſides of the Quadrat, the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures there, wil ſhew you the Northing or Southing, Eaſting or Weſting as the queſtion requires.</p>
               <p>As in this example, becauſe your courſe in general is North-Eaſterly, let the ſide A B repreſent the North Meridian line, ſo the ſide A D, at the bottome, or B C at the top, wil repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the lines of eaſterly longitude or diſtance. Then becauſe your courſe is <hi>N by E,</hi> which is the firſt rumbe from the North Meridian Eaſtward, lay your horn Index upon the firſt rumbe from the line A B, which is the line A P. Then count your diſtance vvhich is one degree or 100 parts upon your Index, and marke vvhere this number ends, vvhich is in the point P, vvhere the line A P croſſeth the arch B P. This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act point vvhere you are. Novv if you trace the line P B that runs through this point to the Meridian line, you ſhall there finde that you are to the Northward of the place A 98 parts of a degree divided into 100 parts, likewiſe if you trace the line that runs through this point P to the bottome or top of the Quadrat, there you ſhal finde that you have altered your longitudes 19/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> parts and a half.</p>
               <p>Having thus found out the exact Northing and Eaſting<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w to ſet the Northing and Eaſting found out, upon the Chart.</note> of this place from A, vve vvil novv to avoid the inſerting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother figure) ſuppoſe this laſt to be a plain chart again, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having each ſide divided into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 degrees as before, and if you ſet dovvn this place by the firſt propoſition of the plain chart, according to the latitude and longitude thus found out, <hi>viz.</hi> latitude 00 degrees 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parts, and longitude 0<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> degrees 19 parts and a halfe, you ſhal finde that its place vvil be cloſe by the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:117362:48"/> corner A, at the figure 1. Likewiſe for your better proceeding afterwards, you may write down the longitude and latitude of this place 1, as you may ſee in the table following.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in the ſame voyage-</note>Now ſuppoſe that you alter your courſe at this place 1, and ſail from hence <hi>N N E,</hi> which is the ſecond rumbe from the Meridian one degree, or 100 parts more. And it is deſired to know the longitude and latitude of this ſecond place.</p>
               <p>To know this lay the Index upon the ſecond rumbe from the Meridian line A B, and count upon it your diſtance ſayled, which is 100 parts, and obſerving wel where this diſtance ends, which is where the line of the ſecond rumbe doth cut the arch B P, which is in the croſſe at 2: this is the point that ſhews you the difference of longitude and latitude of this place from the laſt. Now by the lines that paſſe through this croſſe, you ſhal ſee the difference of latitude to be 92 parts, and the difference of longitude to be 38 parts. Now if you would know the true longitude and latitude of this place, in reſpect of the firſt place A, that ſo you may ſet it down upon your chart; you muſt adde the Northing and Eaſting of both the places toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>From A to 1 <hi>N by E</hi> 100 parts is,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>North</hi> 98.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Eaſt</hi> 19 ½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>From 1 to 2 <hi>N N E</hi> 100 parts is,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N.</hi> 92.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E.</hi> 38</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Summe of both is</cell>
                        <cell>1, 90</cell>
                        <cell>57 ½</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>So that the latitude of this ſecond place is 1 degree 90 parts of North Latitude, and 0 degrees 57 parts and a half of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. And then ſetting it down according to the firſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, of the plain chart, you ſhal finde this place to be at the figure 2 neer the corner A.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſhal finde out the point of any place in your chart more certainly then other ways it is poſſible for you to do, and with leſſe trouble, as you may ſee by the table follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the reſt of the places, 3 4 5 6 7 in the chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Note this well.</note>But here you muſt obſerve that as in theſe places where the latitude and longitude doth ſtil increaſe, you make uſe of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſo if your courſe lies ſo, that the longitude and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude both decreaſeth, you muſt make uſe of Subſtraction both in longitude and latitude. And ſometimes the courſe may lye
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:117362:48"/> ſo, that the longitude may increaſe, and the latitude may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, then you muſt adde the one, and ſubſtract the other. your beſt rule to guide you in this, when to adde and when to ſubſtract is to obſerve your courſe in general, which way it tends, which you may eaſily ſee by your Chart.</p>
               <p>As for example<note place="margin">Example.</note> being come to the place 7 in the chart, whoſe latitude is 4 degrees, 57 parts, and the longitude thereof is 4 degrees, 57 parts, and from this place you ſail <hi>S by W,</hi> that is upon the firſt Rumbe from the Meridian to the Weſtward, 100 parts, and it is deſired to know what longitude &amp; latitude you are then in.</p>
               <p>To perform this, firſt you may ſee by your courſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, which is South-weſterly from the place 7, that both the longitude and latitude of the place you ſail to muſt needs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and therefore the difference of longitude and latitude which you ſhal finde out by the Inſtrument, muſt be ſubſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the longitude and latitude of the place 7, that ſo you may have the true longitude and latitude thereof. Now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conſidered this; by your Quadrat you ſhal finde that the courſe being the firſt rumb from the Meridian, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 parts, the difference of latitude wil be 98 parts, and the difference of longitude 19 parts and a half: this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from the longitude and latitude of 7, ſhews the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude and latitude of the place 8 where you are.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The place 7 hath latitude</cell>
                        <cell>4 deg.</cell>
                        <cell>57 parts. long.</cell>
                        <cell>4 deg.</cell>
                        <cell>57 p.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Subſt. the differ of latitude</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>98 long.</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>19 ½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſt for the place 8 latit.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>59 long.</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>37 ½</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Thus likewiſe you muſt do to finde the longitude of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places 9 10 11 12 13 A.<note n="*" place="margin">A good way for young begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to avoid miſtakes.</note> And it wil be a great help to direct you when to adde, and when to ſubſtract, if you joyn four of theſe Quadrats together, which you may very wel do, if in a large ſheet of paper, you draw a large circle with your compaſſes, and dividing it into four parts, make each of them like to this, and ſet the names of the points of the compaſſe to the rumbes, as in the figure of the compaſſe <hi>page</hi> 10. By this means without any trouble you ſhal plainly ſee the Eaſting
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:117362:49"/> and Weſting, the Northing and Southing of your courſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to ſet down theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in a table.</note>But now for the better ſetting down of theſe diſtances, you muſt divide your table into four columns, for the four princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal quarters, Eaſt, Weſt, North, South, and ſet down therein according to their titles, the Eaſting or Weſting, Northing or Southing of your courſe, which you finde by the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then in caſting up your accounts, you muſt adde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together that you finde under one columne, but if you have any ſummes in contrary columns, as Eaſt and Weſt, or North and South, you muſt ſubſtract the ſumme of the Eaſt from the ſumme of the Weſt; and the ſumme of the North co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne from the ſumme of the South, ſo often as you would finde the longitude and latitude of the place where you are, as you may ſee by this following table of all the voyage out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and homeward.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Courſe.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">diſt. <hi>d pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Nor <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Sou, <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Eaſt <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">weſt <hi>d pa</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Lat. <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Lon <hi>d. pa</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The place A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <note place="margin">Compa e this table and the Chart wel together.</note>from A to 1</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N by E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 1 to 2</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 80</cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1, 90</cell>
                        <cell>0, 58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 2 to 3</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N E by N</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 55</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2, 73</cell>
                        <cell>1, 13</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 3 to 4</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 71</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3, 44</cell>
                        <cell>1, 84</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 4 to 5</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N E by E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 56</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4, 00</cell>
                        <cell>2, 67</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 5 to 6</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4, 38</cell>
                        <cell>3, 59</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 6 to 7</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E by N</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4, 57</cell>
                        <cell>4, 57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 7 to 8</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S by W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell>3, 59</cell>
                        <cell>4, 38</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 8 to 9</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S S W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell>2, 67</cell>
                        <cell>4, 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 9 to 10</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S W by S</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 55</cell>
                        <cell>1, 84</cell>
                        <cell>1, 44</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 10 to 11</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 71</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 71</cell>
                        <cell>1, 13</cell>
                        <cell>2, 73</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 11 to 12</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S W by W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 0</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 56</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell>0, 57</cell>
                        <cell>1, 90</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 12 to 13</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>W S W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 13 to A</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>W by S</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell>0, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:117362:49"/>
               <p>Thus I hope you ſee by this table, how that by adding or ſubſtracting, the Northing, Southing, Eaſting or Weſting, to, or from the longitude and latitude of the place before, you may ſtil finde out the longitude and the latitude of the place you are in, for the keeping of your dead reckoning, as exactly as need be required.</p>
               <p>Now the other Propoſition which is uſeful in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of your account, according to your obſervation is this.<note place="margin">How to find out the true point of your longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the latitude.</note> By the rumbe and the difference of latitude, to finde the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of the place where you are, and the diſtance of this place from the other. Now the way of working this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Quadrat is thus, Firſt, you muſt ſuppoſe one of the ſides to be the meridian line, and the other to be the line of Eaſt or Weſt as before, then lay your Index to the degree of the Rumbe, on which you have ſailed, and keep it there. Then count upon the Meridian line from A, the difference of latitude of this place you are in (according to your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) from the place you came laſt, and note where this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ends, and marke wel the line that is drawn from this place, and trace it to your Index, and this point where this line croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Index, is the point where you are. Now if you count the parts upon your Index from A to this point, ſo you ſhal ſee the true diſtance you have ſayled in that Rumbe. And if you trace the line that runnes through this point to the line of longitude at the top or bottome of the Inſtrument, there you ſhal ſee the difference of your longitude, or rather how farre Eaſtward or Weſtward it is from the former place.</p>
               <p>For example,<note place="margin">Example.</note> ſuppoſe you ſailed from the place A. (whoſe longitude and latitude let be as before) <hi>N by E,</hi> that is upon the firſt Rumbe from the Meridian, ſo long, til by obſervation you found you had altered your latitude 98 parts of a degree divided into 10 parts: and you deſire to know how far you have ſailed in the Rumbe; and how far you are to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the place A.</p>
               <p>Firſt, lay your Index upon the line A P, which is the firſt Rumbe from the Meridian, and keep it there, then count the difference of the latitude, which is 98 parts, in the meridian
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:117362:50"/> line from A to B, then marke the line that is drawn from this part, and obſerve wel where it croſſeth the Index or Rumbe line, which is in the point P, and this is the very point where you are. Now if you count the parts upon your Index from A to this point, you ſhal finde your diſtance ſailed to be 100 parts or one degree. And if you marke the line that runs through this point to the line of longitude, you ſhal there ſee the difference of longitude which is 19 parts and a half to the Eaſtward from A, thus the propoſition is fully reſolved.</p>
               <p>But in this propoſition you muſt take notice, that if you ſail upon ſeveral Rumbes before you obſerve the latitude, then firſt you muſt finde out the Rumbe which lies from your firſt place, to the place where you are according to your dead reckoning (as is ſhewed in the ſixt propoſition of the Plane Chart) and then laying your Index upon this Rumbe, worke as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to work when the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is of more then 100 parts.</note>Note that in working of either of theſe propoſitions by the Quadrat, if the diſtance or difference of latitude be more then a degree or 100 parts, then you may firſt finde out what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to one degree, and then what belongs to the odde parts, and adding them together, you may finde the truth as exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if your Inſtrument were large enough to ſhew both at once. But if your diſtance or difference of latitude be four or five degrres, you may then very wel work the propoſition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your chart, without uſing the Quadrat, and need not fear errour, if you be any thing careful, and work by a true ſcale of rumbes and equal parts.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have ſhewed you how to worke theſe two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon the plane chart,<note place="margin">How to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form theſe two propoſitions in all latitudes.</note> or in places neer the Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctial: But becauſe the degrees of latitude in the true Sea-chart muſt not be all of one and the ſame length, therefore neither can the true latitude nor longitude of places be ſet down by one and the ſame ſcale of equal parts. Therefore I ſhal now ſhew you, how when you have found out the Northing or Southing, Eaſting or Weſting of any place, as is before ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Quadrat, how you ſhal ſet it down in any latitude that it may ſhew the true longitude thereof. For you muſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:117362:50"/> know, that though the Northing and Southing, doth ſhew the true difference of latitude in all latitudes: yet the Eaſting and Weſting found out by the Quadrat, doth not ſhew the true difference of longitude in thoſe places, which are any thing diſtant from the Equinoctiall, I ſhal therefore ſhew you how to performe theſe two Propoſitions in all latitudes.</p>
               <p>For example of the firſt Propoſition.<note place="margin">Firſt, for the dead recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> Suppoſe you were at the place H, in the following figure, whoſe longitude is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firſt Meridian, but it lies in 45 degres of North lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and ſuppoſe you ſhould ſail from this place <hi>N by E</hi> to the diſtance of 100 parts, as before ſaid, and it is deſired to finde the latitude and longitude of this place.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you muſt finde out the Northing and Eaſting by the quadrat as is before ſhewed.<note place="margin">The firſt way to perform this by the Chart it ſelfe.</note> Now the Northing of this courſe being 98 parts, muſt be added to the latitude of the former place 45 degrees, ſo the latitude you are in wil be known to be 45 degrees, 98 parts, then lay your ruler to this latitude in the ſides of your chart, and draw a ſhort line <hi>a</hi> 1, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how much the Eaſting of your place is, which in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is 19 parts and a half, take this diſtance with your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes out of the ſcale of latitude, about the middle latitude between theſe two places, and then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in the Meridian of H at <hi>a,</hi> with the other croſſe the line <hi>a</hi> 1 at 1, and ſo you ſhal ſet down the place according to its true longitude which is 00 degrees, 28 parts from the Meridian of H, as you may ſee by the chart: and not 19 parts, and a half, as before it was under the Equinoctial, or by the plain chart.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Thus in this example, the middle latitude between the two places being 45 degrees, 50 parts, draw the line A <hi>c</hi> D by this latitude, &amp; then counting the Eaſting of this courſe, which is 19 parts &amp; a half in the ſide <hi>a b,</hi> the line <hi>b c</hi> drawn from thence wil croſſe the former line of the middle latitude at <hi>c,</hi> then ſetting one foot of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſes in this point at <hi>c,</hi> &amp; opening the other to the center A, this diſtance A meaſured in the ſcale A B wil ſhew 28 parts, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the true difference of the longitude of the place 1 from the Meridian of H. And if thus you wil make trial, you ſhal finde out the longitudes and latitudes of all the other places, 2 3 4 5, &amp;c. as they are ſet down in the table following.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Courſe.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">diſt. <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Nor <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Sou, <hi>d pa</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Eaſt <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">weſt <hi>d pa</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Latit. <hi>de. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">(*) <hi>d. pa.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Lon. <hi>d. pa</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The place H</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>45, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from H to 1</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N by E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>45, 98</cell>
                        <cell>0, 28</cell>
                        <cell>0, 28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 1 to 2</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>46, 90</cell>
                        <cell>0, 74</cell>
                        <cell>0, 82</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 2 to 3</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N E by N</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 55</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>47, 73</cell>
                        <cell>0, 82</cell>
                        <cell>1, 64</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 3 to 4</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 1</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 71</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>48, 44</cell>
                        <cell>1, 06</cell>
                        <cell>2, 70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 4 to 5</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>N E by E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 56</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>49, 00</cell>
                        <cell>1, 24</cell>
                        <cell>3, 94</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 5 to 6</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E N E</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>49, 38</cell>
                        <cell>1, 41</cell>
                        <cell>5, 35</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 6 to 7</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>E by N</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>49, 57</cell>
                        <cell>1, 50</cell>
                        <cell>6, 85</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 7 to 8</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S by W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell>48, 59</cell>
                        <cell>0, 30</cell>
                        <cell>6, 55</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 8 to 9</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S S W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 38</cell>
                        <cell>47, 67</cell>
                        <cell>0, 57</cell>
                        <cell>5, 98</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>from 9 to 10</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>SW by S</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell>47, 84</cell>
                        <cell>0, 82</cell>
                        <cell>5, 16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 10 to 11</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 71</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 71</cell>
                        <cell>46, 13</cell>
                        <cell>, 102</cell>
                        <cell>4, 14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 11 to 12</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>SW by W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 0</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 56</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 83</cell>
                        <cell>45, 57</cell>
                        <cell>1. 19</cell>
                        <cell>2, 95</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 12 to 13</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>W S W</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 8</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 92</cell>
                        <cell>45, 19</cell>
                        <cell>1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>1</cell>
                        <cell>1, 64</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 13 to 14</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>W by S</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1, 00</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 19</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 98</cell>
                        <cell>45 00</cell>
                        <cell>1, 39</cell>
                        <cell>0, 25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to H</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Weſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0, 7</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0, 17</cell>
                        <cell>45, 00</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, 25</cell>
                        <cell>0, 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:117362:52"/>
               <p>This table agrees with the former in moſt things, the chief difference is in the longitude,<note place="margin">Note the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this Table from the former.</note> which muſt be thus found out. By the Eaſting or Weſting of your courſe, you muſt finde out the difference of longitude thereof according to the middle latitude, and ſet it in the table under the laſt column, but one, noted thus (*) and this difference added or ſubſtracted as it ought to be in the laſt columne, ſhews the true longitude of the place where you are. This wil be your beſt way to keep your dead reckoning.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes.</note>Now for the ſecond propoſition, which is by the Rumbe, and the difference of latitude; to finde the difference of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, and the diſtance. To perform this, firſt knowing the latitudes of the two places, draw a line in your Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant of latitude, by the middle latitude of the two places. Then count the difference of latitude in the ſcale of the quadrant of latitude, A B, and where the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ends, draw or obſerve the line drawn from it, where it croſſeth the line of the middle latitude, then taking this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in your compaſſes, meaſure it in the ſcale A B (increaſed if need be) then work with this number upon the quadrat as is ſhewed before <hi>page</hi> 89, as if this number were the true diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of latitude between the two places, ſo you ſhal finde out the true difference of longitude in degrees and parts. And for the true diſtance, if you obſerve the parts of the Index of the quadrat at theſe points, and then meaſure them in the line of the middle latitude, the line that runs from this point to the ſcale of the quadrant, wil ſhew the true diſtance.</p>
               <p>For example, let the place from which you ſail be H, in the latitude of 45 degrees, let the Rumbe you ſail upon be <hi>N by E</hi> and let the difference of latitude be 98 parts; and it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to finde the true difference of longitude, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this point.</p>
               <p>Firſt in the quadrant of latitude, draw the line A Z, by the middle latitude of the two places; which is 45 degrees, 49 parts, then in the ſcale of the quadrant A B (counting the whole ſcale or Radius for one degree) reckoning the difference of latitude 98, and obſerve the parallel line that comes from
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:117362:52"/> this where it croſſeth the line of the middle latitude which is at Z. Then ſetting one foot of your compaſſes in this point Z, open the other to the center A, and meaſure this diſtance in the ſcale A B lengthened, and you ſhal find it to be 140 parts: thus the true difference of latitude 98 parts is inlarged to 140 parts, which is the proportion it ought to have in this latitude. Then working with this difference of latitude inlarged upon the quadrat, as was ſhew'd <hi>pag.</hi> 89. &amp; 90, firſt, for 100 parts, I find the difference of longitude to be 20 parts, and the diſtance upon the Index is 102 parts, then likewiſe for the 40 parts; I finde the difference of longitude to be 8 parts, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance on the Index is almoſt 41 parts. Theſe two ſummes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together makes the true difference of longitude to be 28 parts, and the diſtance 143 parts almoſt. Now, laſtly, this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance meaſured in the line of the middle latitude, in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant of latitude, wil reach from A to D, and the line that runs from this place up to the ſcale A B ſhews the true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſailed, which is one degree or 100 parts.</p>
               <p>Thus having found out by obſervation at any time the true latitude of the place where you are, if it ſhal differ from your latitude by dead reckoning, you may finde exactly in what point you are in reſpect of the longitude as wel as the latitude. And though ſome of theſe things may ſeem at the firſt a little difficult; yet if you conſider wel, all that hath bin ſaid before and ſo underſtand the firſt principles of the Worke, you ſhal finde, that a little practiſing of theſe queſtions, and ſome ſuch like, which you may propoſe to your ſelfe, wil make all very plain and eaſie.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
